<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28817665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5560670</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-17-09638</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age Groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject><subj-group><subject>Infants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Families</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject><subj-group><subject>Infants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Analytical Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Trace Elements</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Elements</subject><subj-group><subject>Manganese</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Elements</subject><subj-group><subject>Lead (Element)</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Elements</subject><subj-group><subject>Arsenic</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Elements</subject><subj-group><subject>Zinc</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Africa</subject><subj-group><subject>Namibia</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical locations</subject><subj-group><subject>South America</subject><subj-group><subject>Argentina</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Concentrations of trace elements in human milk: Comparisons among women in Argentina, Namibia, Poland, and the United States</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Trace elements in human milk</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7287-8029</contrib-id><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Laura D.</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breakey</surname><given-names>Alicia A.</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scelza</surname><given-names>Brooke</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valeggia</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jasienska</surname><given-names>Grazyna</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hinde</surname><given-names>Katie</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Human Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Anthropology, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Environmental Health, Faculty of Health Sciences, Jagiellonian University, Krakow, Poland</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff005"><label>5</label>
<addr-line>Center for Evolution and Medicine, Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff006"><label>6</label>
<addr-line>School of Human Evolution and Social Change, Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gallyas</surname><given-names>Ferenc</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of PECS Medical School, HUNGARY</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>lauraklein@fas.harvard.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e0183367</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 Klein et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Klein et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0183367.pdf"/><abstract><p>Human milk contains essential micronutrients for growth and development during early life. Environmental pollutants, such as potentially toxic metals, can also be transferred to the infant through human milk. These elements have been well-studied, but changing diets and environments and advances in laboratory technology require re-examining these elements in a variety of settings. The aim of this study was to characterize the concentrations of essential and toxic metals in human milk from four diverse populations. Human milk samples (n = 70) were collected in Argentina (n = 21), Namibia (n = 6), Poland (n = 23), and the United States (n = 20) using a standardized mid-feed collection procedure. Milk concentrations of calcium, zinc, iron, copper, manganese, lead, arsenic, and cadmium were determined using inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS). We used standard multiple linear regression models to evaluate differences among populations, while including infant age, infant sex, and maternal parity status (multiparous or primiparous) as covariates. Concentrations of all elements, except zinc, varied across populations after controlling for infant age, infant sex, and maternal parity. Calcium and magnesium showed more differences across populations than iron or copper. There were no significant differences among population in zinc concentrations. Mean concentrations of lead, but not arsenic, were low compared to recently published values from other populations. The concentrations of trace elements in human milk are variable among populations. Limitations due to small sample sizes and environmental contamination of some samples prevent us from drawing robust conclusions about the causes of these differences.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id><institution>National Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BCS-0952264</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Valeggia</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by funding from the Harvard University Department of Human Evolutionary Biology awarded to LDK, AAB, and KH; the Harvard GSAS Graduate Society [Summer Predissertation Fellowship] awarded to LDK; Jagiellonian University [K/ZDS/006 113] awarded to GJ; and the National Science Foundation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov">www.nsf.gov</ext-link>) [BCS-0952264] to CV. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Human milk is considered the ideal food for infant nutrition. In addition to macronutrients, human milk also contains micronutrients, including trace minerals. Many of these elements are essential for growth and development during early life as micronutrient deficiencies during early life adversely affect individual and community health [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Micronutrient deficiencies are associated with more frequent infections in the short-term and increased rates of chronic diseases and reduced work productivity in the long-term [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, excessive amounts of these elements can also be detrimental. High levels of iron in formula may increase an infant&#x02019;s risk of infection by increasing nutrient bioavailability to pathogenic bacteria [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and high manganese exposure in children has been associated with impaired cognitive development and motor coordination [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Determining appropriate intake levels of micronutrients during early life is of substantial importance for public health recommendations and clinical interventions. Thus, exploring the variation of milk bioactives in human milk within and across populations is particularly necessary [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>In addition to essential elements, milk can also transfer potentially toxic metals, such as lead, arsenic, and cadmium. These metals have been detected in milk around the world, though concentrations can vary widely depending on environmental exposures like diet, the use of leaded gasoline, or smoking [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Toxic metals do not generally accumulate in human milk even when present in maternal circulation and postnatal exposure via milk ingestion is likely lower than fetal exposure [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Early-life exposures, however, can contribute to long-lasting adverse health outcomes, such as neurodevelopmental disorders [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and impaired immune and respiratory function [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Moreover, environmental exposures to toxic metals often disproportionately affect marginalized groups [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Concerns about pollutants in human milk can also affect infant feeding decisions [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Although decades of research effort has been allocated to human milk concentrations of micronutrients and toxic metals, dietary shifts, environmental changes, and more sensitive analytical technologies motivate sustained investigation [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For example, human milk lead levels in Sweden decreased significantly from 1989 to 2009, likely as a result of the ban on leaded gasoline use [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, levels of toxic elements in human milk remain high in many areas around the world [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Cinar and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] reported that some of the highest levels of toxic metals in human milk in Turkey were found in rural, not urban or industrial areas. In the US and Canada, tribal lands are protected by fewer environmental regulations than non-tribal lands, and experience greater environmental degradation and pollution [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Many traditional populations are experiencing varying degrees of market integration or urbanization, which can be associated with changes in diet and/or environmental exposures [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Due to the importance of adequate micronutrient intake in early life for individual and community health, and changing diets and environments worldwide, the study of human milk trace elements remains relevant to research in human lactation and public health. Here we characterize the concentrations of five essential and three toxic elements in human milk as it is typically consumed across diverse populations from Argentina, Poland, the US, and Namibia. Samples from Argentina and Namibia were collected in indigenous populations. Previous studies have understandably focused on populations that are severely malnourished, at high risk for toxic metal exposure, or are in urban areas of wealthy nations. By contrast, the range of geography and lifestyle represented by the populations in this study attempts to reflect the breadth of modern human environments, including populations that are not well-represented in the current literature.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><p>Samples for this project were collected as part of a larger investigation of the composition of human milk across diverse populations. A standardized collection procedure was used to facilitate comparison across populations. Participants for whom at least 2 ml of milk sample remained after other planned analyses were included in present report. Milk samples were divided into aliquots shortly after collection, thus, the composition of the subsample analyzed here is expected to be an unbiased representation of the full sample from each individual. Study procedures were approved by the Harvard Committee on the Use of Human Subjects (#23868, #21979, #13&#x02013;0900), the University of Pennsylvania Institutional Review Board (#811200), and the University of California Los Angeles Institutional Review Board (#13&#x02013;000881). No formal ethical approval was required at the local level in Argentina or Poland, though permission to conduct research was obtained from the village priest in Poland. Research in Namibia was conducted under research visa (#W830312013) and local approval was also granted by the Chief of the area. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants except those in Namibia, where informed oral consent was obtained from each participant and the participant&#x02019;s head of household because the population is illiterate. Documentation of oral consent was not required, as it was implicit that the start of the oral interview meant that oral consent had been given.</p><sec id="sec003"><title>Participants</title><p>Milk samples were provided by lactating mothers (N = 70) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0183367.t001">Table 1</xref>). Inclusion criteria were mothers nursing biological offspring produced from a singleton pregnancy and no indication of mastitis at the time of milk collection. Mothers of infants under two weeks of age or over two years of age were excluded from the study. No participants were current smokers.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0183367.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic characteristics of sample.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0183367.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0183367.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Argentina</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 20)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 6)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 21)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 70)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infant Sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infant Age, days <italic>M</italic>(<italic>SD</italic>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (101)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239 (194)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (100)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (107)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (112)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal Parity Status</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Primiparous</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Multiparous</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity <italic>M</italic>(<italic>SD</italic>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (2.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (2.1)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Settings</title><p>Samples were collected in a variety of contexts. Women living in the Boston area provided human milk samples from June to August 2013 and represent an urban W.E.I.R.D. (Westernized, educated, industrial, rich, democratic) population [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Polish samples were collected at the Mogielica Human Ecology Study Site, a group of rural villages in southern Poland [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], during July and August 2012. This region has historically engaged in small-scale agriculture, but is increasingly transitioning to participation in wage labor. Most people live in modern houses and all have access to professional health care [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Argentinean samples were collected from indigenous Qom (formerly Toba) women in northeastern Argentina from September 2012 to March 2013. Traditionally, the Qom people were hunter-gathers, but today many have migrated to poor peri-urban barrios where they have access to free governmental healthcare, but often share outdoor water taps and lack indoor toilets [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Namibian samples were collected from indigenous Himba women living in northern Namibia during September 2013. The Himba people are semi-nomadic agro-pastoralists. There is one small medical clinic a day&#x02019;s walk from the study area and a communal water tap, but the community lacks plumbing and electricity [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Data collection</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Demographic information</title><p>Maternal parity, infant age, and infant sex were self-reported by the mother during guided oral interviews in the participant&#x02019;s native language.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Milk collection</title><p>A single, mid-feed milk sample was provided by each mother [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Samples were collected between 8AM and 11:30AM. Participants were asked not to feed the infant from the sample breast for approximately 2 hours before collection. Participants self-expressed by hand a milk sample up to 10 ml into polypropylene BD Falcon tubes (#352070). Samples were then gently mixed by hand and aliquoted into Axygen cryovials (#22&#x02013;269). Samples were frozen at -20&#x000b0;C (in Argentina and Namibia) or -80&#x000b0;C (in Poland and the US) shortly after collection. Samples from outside the US were shipped to Harvard University on dry ice and frozen at -80&#x000b0;C until analysis. Mineral and metal content is stable through freeze/thaw cycles [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Data analysis</title><sec id="sec009"><title>Milk trace metal analysis</title><p>Milk calcium (Ca), zinc (Zn), iron (Fe), copper (Cu), manganese (Mn), arsenic (As), lead (Pb), and cadmium (Cd) in milk were analyzed at The Trace Metals Lab at the Harvard School of Public Health. Briefly, 1 to 2 ml of sample was measured on an analytical balance and 1 mL of ultrapure nitric acid (BDH Aristar Ultra) was added to each sample. Samples were then digested with a Milestone Ultrawave microwave digestion system, diluted with deionized water to a final volume of 10 ml, and analyzed with a Perkin Elmer ELAN DRC II ICP Mass Spectrometer. Cadmium levels were below the level of detection for all samples and therefore excluded from analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Population differences in metal levels were evaluated by standard multiple linear regression models. All analyses were conducted in R version 3.3.0. Pearson correlation coefficients and p-values were determined using the &#x0201c;Hmisc&#x0201d; package. Data were graphically inspected for normality. To normalize data distributions, Fe, Pb, and As concentrations were Box-Cox transformed and Zn, Cu, and Mn concentrations were natural log transformed before analysis. Calcium concentrations were approximately normally distributed and thus not transformed. Infant age (in days), infant sex, and maternal parity (coded as multiparous or primiparous) were included as covariates in all models. Post-hoc pairwise comparisons were conducted with the &#x0201c;lsmeans&#x0201d; package and adjusted for multiple comparisons using the Holm method. Alpha was set at 0.05 and all p-values presented are two-tailed.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec011"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec012"><title>Correlations among trace elements</title><p>To determine whether differences in milk micronutrient levels between populations might be due to a dilution effect, correlations among the trace elements were calculated. Correlations between trace element concentrations across all 70 samples ranged from weakly negative to moderately positive. Calcium was positively correlated to iron (<italic>r</italic> = 0.41, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) and copper (<italic>r</italic> = 0.42, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) but negatively correlated with lead (<italic>r</italic> = -0.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) and arsenic (<italic>r</italic> = -0.3, <italic>p</italic> = 0.01). Zinc was positively correlated to copper (<italic>r</italic> = 0.39, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001). Lead was positively correlated with iron (<italic>r</italic> = 0.29, <italic>p</italic> = 0.016), manganese (<italic>r</italic> = 0.26, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03), and arsenic (<italic>r</italic> = 0.29, <italic>p</italic> = 0.01). Arsenic was also positively correlated to manganese (<italic>r</italic> = 0.4, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Infant and maternal characteristics</title><p>Calcium, iron, zinc, and copper concentrations in milk decreased with infant age (Ca: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = -0.46, <italic>t</italic> = -5.39, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001; Fe: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = -0.50, <italic>t</italic> = -5.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001; Zn: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = -0.57, <italic>t</italic> = -5.63, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001; Cu: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = -0.58, <italic>t</italic> = -6.20, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001). Infant age was not significantly associated with manganese, lead, or arsenic concentrations. Infant sex did not significantly predict mineral concentrations in any model (<italic>p</italic>&#x02265;0.10 for all). Similarly maternal primiparity was not associated with trace mineral concentration in milk, although primiparous mothers tended to produce milk with higher levels of iron than did multiparous mothers (<italic>M</italic> &#x000b1; <italic>SD</italic>: 1.17 &#x000b1; 0.28 mg/L vs 1.10 &#x000b1; 0.38 mg/L, respectively, <italic>t</italic>(60) = 1.89, <italic>p</italic> = 0.06).</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Differences among populations</title><p>The concentrations of elements in human milk were variable, both within and among populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0183367.t002">Table 2</xref>). All comparisons are controlled for infant age, sex, and maternal parity status (primiparous or multiparous). The trace mineral profile of human milk samples often differed among populations, but not always in the same directions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0183367.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0183367.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Summary of trace element concentrations.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0183367.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0183367.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Argentina</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trace Element</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 20)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 6)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n = 21)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 70)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Calcium (mg/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268.72</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.83</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227.06</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.79</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.34</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.67</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.72</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.62</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.02</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.69</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.94</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.47</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.95</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.21</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293.71</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304.47</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Iron (mg/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Zinc (mg/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Copper (&#x003bc;g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.52</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.94</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.87</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211.04</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.06</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.49</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.48</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.95</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.52</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">317.09</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.83</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252.42</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419.09</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Manganese (&#x003bc;g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.78</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.27</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.24</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Arsenic (&#x003bc;g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.08</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Lead (&#x003bc;g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0183367.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Pairwise comparisons of trace element concentrations between populations.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0183367.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0183367.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Calcium</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Zinc</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Iron</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Manganese</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Copper</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Arsenic</underline></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><underline>Lead</underline></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contrast</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> (63)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US&#x02014;Namibia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.634</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US&#x02014;Poland</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US&#x02014;Argentina</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia&#x02014;Poland</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.803</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia&#x02014;Argentina</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland&#x02014;Argentina</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; .001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Of the essential trace elements, calcium and manganese differed most among populations. Calcium concentrations were significantly lower in the Namibian population than all others (US: <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001; Poland: <italic>p</italic> = 0.003; Argentina: <italic>p</italic> = 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183367.g001">Fig 1</xref>). US milk samples had higher calcium levels than did samples from Poland (<italic>p</italic> = 0.003), but not Argentina. Mean manganese concentrations were 3 to 4 times higher in the Namibian and Argentinian samples compared to the US (US-Namibia: <italic>p</italic> = &#x0003c; .0001; US-Argentina: <italic>p</italic> = 0.0008) or Polish (Poland-Namibia: <italic>p</italic> = &#x0003c;0.0001; Poland-Argentina: <italic>p</italic> = &#x0003c;0.0001) samples. There was no significant difference in manganese concentrations between the Namibian and Argentinian samples, but the US had higher levels than the Polish (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0008) samples.</p><fig id="pone.0183367.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Calcium, iron, and lead in breast milk from four populations.</title><p>This figure illustrates the concentrations of (A) calcium, (B) iron, and (C) lead measured in breast milk in samples from the US, Namibia, Poland, and Argentina. Each point illustrates an individual sample value, and the bold horizontal line in each box plot depicts the median for each population. Letters indicate statistically significant differences among population means (p&#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0183367.g001"/></fig><p>Iron, zinc, and copper showed fewer differences among populations. Iron levels in the US and Namibian samples were higher than those from Poland (US-Poland: <italic>p</italic> = 0.001; Namibia-Poland: <italic>p</italic> = 0.003) and Argentina (US-Argentina: <italic>p</italic> = 0.019; Namibia-Argentina: <italic>p</italic> = 0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183367.g001">Fig 1</xref>). However, iron levels were not significantly different between US and Namibian samples or Polish and Argentinian samples. There were no significant differences in zinc concentration among populations, though concentrations in the Argentinian samples tended to be higher than in the US samples (<italic>p</italic> = 0.07). Copper concentrations were highest in the Argentinian samples, and were significantly higher than in the US (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03) and Namibian (<italic>p</italic> = 0.018), but not Polish (<italic>p</italic> = 0.19) samples. There were no significant differences in copper concentrations among the US, Polish, and Namibian samples (all <italic>p</italic>&#x02265;0.19).</p><p>Arsenic and lead were present in samples from all populations. Namibia had significantly higher arsenic concentrations than Argentina (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0191), Poland (<italic>p</italic> = &#x0003c;0.001) and the US (<italic>p</italic> = &#x0003c;0.0001). US arsenic concentrations were significantly lower than Argentinian (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001) samples, but were not significantly different from the Polish (<italic>p</italic> = 0.07). There was also no significant difference between the Polish and Argentinian (<italic>p</italic> = 0.06) samples. Lead levels were significantly lower in the Argentinian samples compared to all other populations (US: <italic>p</italic> = 0.01; Poland: <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001; Namibia: <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183367.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The US had lower lead levels than Namibia (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01), but there was no significant difference between lead concentrations in Poland and the US (<italic>p</italic> = 0.06) or Namibia (p = 0.11).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we characterized the concentrations of five trace elements (Ca, Zn, Fe, Cu, Mn) and two toxic elements (As, Pb) across diverse populations in the United States, Argentina, Poland, and Namibia. Calcium, iron, zinc, and copper concentrations decreased across lactation, but there was no relationship between infant age and manganese, lead, or arsenic. Neither infant sex nor maternal parity status was significantly associated with any trace mineral concentration. The concentrations of elements in human milk were variable both within and among populations, and no population had consistently higher or lower levels of the essential or toxic elements. Calcium and manganese differed more among populations while zinc, iron, and copper showed no or fewer differences among populations, perhaps reflecting common physiological mechanisms to avoid severe deficits of these essential micronutrients. Arsenic and lead were present in samples from all populations.</p><p>Calcium and manganese concentrations differed more among populations compared to other essential trace elements in the present study. This is consistent with previous reports that have found high variation in the reported values of both elements (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0183367.t004">Table 4</xref>). Previously reported mean calcium concentrations have ranged from 84 to 462 mg/L, with a median of 252 mg/L [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Population-level mean calcium concentrations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0183367.t002">Table 2</xref>) in this study fell within this range and were similar to unsupplemented Gambian mothers [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and slightly less than recently reported values from Swedish mothers [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Lower values observed here could be explained in part by the older ages of infant included in the present study, as calcium concentrations in milk progressively decrease after 12 weeks post-partum [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Samples in this study were collected between 2 weeks and 17 months postpartum, while the Swedish and Gambian samples were collected at 2&#x02013;3 and 13 weeks postpartum, respectively. In contrast to calcium, manganese concentrations in milk are very low (4&#x02013;8 &#x003bc;g/L) [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Ranges in manganese concentrations in this study showed 3 to 4 fold differences among populations, which is consistent with previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Notably, manganese was the only essential trace element in our study that was not significantly related to infant age. Casey and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] reported that manganese concentrations became irregular during gradual weaning. Since the average age of all infants in our study is approximately 7 months (<italic>M</italic> &#x000b1; <italic>SD</italic>: 214 &#x000b1; 111 days), most are expected to be receiving complementary foods and are likely to be at various stages of the weaning process.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0183367.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183367.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Trace element concentrations reported in mature human milk.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0183367.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0183367.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trace Element</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis Method<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M</italic>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Calcium&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gambia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl thymol blue</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.93<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1170</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nigeria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thermo Labsystems Arsenazo III Kit</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Copper</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Honduras</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuwait</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-OES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.446<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Iron</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Honduras</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1155</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuwait</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-OES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.072<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="right" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Manganese</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuwait</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-OES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Zinc</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0462</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Honduras</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1165</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuwait</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.471</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-OES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.454</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.970</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-AES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Arsenic</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">602</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slovenia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Lead</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.65</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.59</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palestine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.33</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-MS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICP-OES</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ug/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> Abbreviations: AAS = Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, GF AAS = Graphite Furnace Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, ICP-AES = Inductively Coupled Plasma Atomic Emission Spectroscopy, ICP-MS = Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometry, ICP-OES = Inductively Coupled Plasma Optical Emission Spectrometry</p></fn><fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>b</sup> Means have been standardized to a common unit for each element.</p></fn><fn id="t004fn003"><p><sup>c</sup> Weighted population mean calculated with data reported for sub-groups.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Iron, zinc, and copper tended to be more consistent among populations. Unlike calcium, which is largely associated with citrate or casein in human milk [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], these metals tend to be bound to milk proteins. Iron is largely bound to fat-globule associated proteins or lactoferrin [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], while zinc and copper tend to be bound to whey proteins, including serum albumin [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Human milk is typically low in iron, with a mean around 0.6 mg/L in early lactation that steadily decreases to a mean between 0.2&#x02013;0.3 mg/L after 5&#x02013;6 months [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In the present study, however, mean population concentrations were 1.5 to 4 fold higher. Values in our study are higher than most previously reported values, but are similar to values from Turkey [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] but are still 1.5 to 7 fold lower than typical infant formula levels in Europe or the US [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. We found that primiparous mothers produced slightly higher concentrations of milk iron than did multiparous mothers. This is consistent with previous studies report no relationship between parity and iron concentrations in mature milk [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our results are generally consistent with studies that reported no differences based on location, race, or population or attributable to differences in milk volume ([<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] but see [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]). Milk copper levels in this study fell within the range of previously reported concentrations from Sweden [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], Honduras [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], the US [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and Brazil [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The consistency of concentrations across populations despite the range of geography and lifestyle likely reflects the importance of these trace elements for proper development and function, and common physiological mechanisms to maintain adequate levels for the infant.</p><p>Mean population levels of toxic metals were low across all populations in this study. The World Health Organization set a safety limit of human milk lead concentration between 2 and 5 &#x003bc;g/L [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In this study, only Namibia had a mean lead concentration greater than 2 &#x003bc;g/L. Lead concentrations are comparable to mean levels found in mature milk in Sweden [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and industrial areas in Taiwan [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Lead concentrations in this study are also lower than recently reported values from urban and rural areas in Iraq [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and Turkey [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Mean arsenic concentrations were all below the EPA and WHO recommended limit of 0.01 mg/L in drinking water [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. However, the values we observed are 2 to 5 fold higher than recently published values from Taiwan and Sweden, which both found milk arsenic concentrations &#x0003c;1 &#x003bc;g/L [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Population differences in the concentrations of these trace elements, particularly the toxic metals, may be due to differences in environmental exposures. Arsenic exposure primarily occurs through drinking water or food, and naturally high groundwater levels of arsenic occur in several countries, including Argentina and the US [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Higher levels of lead in human milk have been reported in women that live closer to industrial [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] or urban areas [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], or use cosmetics containing lead [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, risk factors for toxic metal exposure were not directly assessed in this study. Dietary differences among populations are unlikely to explain much of the variation observed in this study. Milk manganese concentrations covaried with maternal dietary intake in one study [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] but iron, zinc, and copper have not been found to relate to maternal dietary intake [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Similarly, most studies have not found an effect of dietary intake on milk calcium levels [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>Population differences in essential milk element concentrations may represent local adaptations to their immediate environments [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Understanding local adaptations has direct implications for the clinical management of public health interventions. More than 2 billion people worldwide are estimated to have micronutrient deficiencies [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and supplementation efforts to improve health outcomes, particularly around pregnancy and lactation, are a major focus of public health research [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. However, appropriate levels of supplementation may not be uniform across populations and supplementation interventions have had unintended adverse consequences. For example, Gambian women had lower bone density during and for years after lactation after receiving calcium supplementation during pregnancy [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, there were no discernable benefits for infant health [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In another study, Kenyan infants who received iron-fortified porridge experienced higher levels of intestinal pathogens and inflammation [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Public health interventions are motivated by the best intentions to improve the current health of individuals and communities, but must consider local adaptations and intergenerational effects to be successful in the long-term.</p><p>This report represents several limitations of scope. As part of a larger research effort measuring multiple milk bioactives, only a subset of participants provided sufficient volume for all planned analyses, biasing inclusion toward participants producing the highest milk volume at the time of sample collection. This assessment of volume, however, remains relative and not absolute, as challenging research settings complicate reliable, standardized measurement of milk volume. Mid-feed milk samples, rather than full mammary evacuations, were used to minimize the nutritional impact to the infant in potentially nutritionally-stressed populations in our study [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Reliable volume measures would better enable us to speak to total potential transfer to the infant, which may be a more biologically meaningful measure, as milk volume may be more sensitive to changes in maternal condition than milk composition [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. However, if population differences in trace metal concentrations reflected a dilution effect, we would expect concentrations of all elements to be positively correlated. Correlation coefficients of mineral concentrations in our study, however, ranged from negative to positive. This suggests our results are unlikely to be explained as simply a dilution effect, though more systematic analysis using a marker protein concentration would be required to definitively eliminate this possibility. These correlations are also unlikely to be a byproduct of differences in casein content. Casein micelles in milk contain the majority of milk&#x02019;s calcium content, but less than 15% of the other essential minerals [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Moreover, comparisons of mineral concentrations across populations did not reveal consistent patterns of higher or lower concentrations, which suggests that these differences are not due to different mean volumes across populations.</p><p>The Namibian samples included in this study require special considerations. Concentrations of most elements measured in this study, with the exceptions of calcium and copper, were highest in the Namibian samples. The sample size for this population, however, was small (n = 6) and some Namibian milk samples were visibly &#x0201c;contaminated&#x0201d; with <italic>otjize</italic>. A traditional cosmetic paste made of clarified butter (or when that is unavailable, petroleum jelly) and red ochre, <italic>otjize</italic> is applied daily to the hair and skin, including the breasts [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Red ochre gets its coloration from iron oxides, though the composition of ochres differs depending on its geographic origin [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Ochre used by the Himba is mainly composed of iron-ore, with trace amounts of other elements, including calcium, manganese, and copper [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Ochres have been utilized extensively across cultures and throughout human history for both symbolic and practical uses, including by the Himba for tanning hides, as sun protection and as an insect repellant [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. While &#x0201c;contamination&#x0201d; of the human milk samples with <italic>otjize</italic> limits our ability to assess the maternal transfer of elements, our results reflect that Namibian infants are likely ingesting micronutrients through milk and suckling contact and very likely represent what these infants are typically consuming. Thus, we have chosen to not exclude the &#x0201c;contaminated&#x0201d; Namibian samples from analysis as, for this population, this composition is likely to be most relevant for considering infant outcomes. We do not yet understand if or how trace metals from <italic>otjize</italic> may be used by the infant or commensal microbes, but these results highlight the importance of evaluating mother&#x02019;s milk within the context of cultural ecology.</p><p>Understanding the range of variation of essential metals in human milk will help to determine the most physiologically relevant concentrations to inform guidelines for supplementation and the production of infant formula. Levels of minerals in infant formula are often higher than in human milk because formula production must also consider differences in bioavailability and loss during production and storage [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. However, the levels of minerals in formula can be much as ten times higher than in human milk [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Today, a variety of analytical techniques, such as ICP-MS, allow for sensitive, reliable, and cost-effective determination of multiple micronutrients from a small-volume sample [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. There is now a growing body of literature to address the need to determine current concentrations of trace essential and toxic elements in populations around the world (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0183367.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0183367.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]). Further studies will be needed to add robust datasets from diverse populations to these new values.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The concentrations of essential and potentially toxic elements in human milk are variable among populations. Due to small sample sizes, our study is limited in its ability to make definitive conclusions about the causes of these differences. However, our study is able to add information about the range of trace metal concentrations in diverse contemporary populations using modern, sensitive laboratory methods.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec017"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0183367.s001"><label>S1 Dataset</label><caption><title>Human milk trace metal concentrations.</title><p>(CSV)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0183367.s001.csv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Steven Worthington at the Harvard Institutive for Quantitative Social Sciences for assistance developing the statistical analysis and Peter Ellison for helpful comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0183367.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Microminerals in human and animal milk</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Handbook of Milk Composition</source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year> pp. <fpage>622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of global micronutrient deficiencies</article-title>. <source>Ann Nutr Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>66</volume>(<issue>S2</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1159/000371618">10.1159/000371618</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Too much of a good thing: an evolutionary argument for decreased iron fortification of infant formula in the United States</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.22476">10.1002/ajhb.22476</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neal</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Manganese toxicity upon overexposure: a decade in review</article-title>. <source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>328</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40572-015-0056-x">10.1007/s40572-015-0056-x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lassek</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaulin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geraghtly</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Fatty acid composition in the mature milk of Bolivian forager&#x02010;horticulturalists: controlled comparisons with a US sample</article-title>. <source>Matern Child Nutr</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>404</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1740-8709.2012.00412.x">10.1111/j.1740-8709.2012.00412.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22624983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chemical Contaminants in Breast Milk: Time Trends and Regional Variability</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>110</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>a339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>a347</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.021100339">10.1289/ehp.021100339</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gurbay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charehsaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eken</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sayal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girgin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yurdakok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Toxic metals in breast milk samples from Ankara, Turkey: Assessment of lead, cadmium, nickel, and arsenic levels</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>149</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12011-012-9400-2">10.1007/s12011-012-9400-2</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22528772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>F&#x000e4;ngstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nermell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuenstl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goessler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (2008). <article-title>Breast-feeding protects against arsenic exposure in Bangladeshi infants</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>969</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/eph.11094">10.1289/eph.11094</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hylkema</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Early-life exposure to widespread environmental toxicants and health risk: A focus on the immune and respiratory systems</article-title>. <source>Ann Glob Health</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>82</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aogh.2016.01.023">10.1016/j.aogh.2016.01.023</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27325070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waghiyi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Indigenous Peoples of North America: Environmental Exposures and Reproductive Justice</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>120</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1649</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.1205422">10.1289/ehp.1205422</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shawahna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zyoud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dwikat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El-Helo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yacoub</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hilal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast milk lead levels in 3 major regions of the West Bank of Palestine</article-title>. <source>J Hum Lact</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0890334416646566">10.1177/0890334416646566</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27161259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rklund</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vahter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grand&#x000e9;r</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lignell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metals and trace element concentrations in breast milk of first time healthy mothers: a biological monitoring study</article-title>. <source>Environ Health</source>. <year>2012</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1476-069X-11-92">10.1186/1476-069X-11-92</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cinar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ozdemir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yucel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ucar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>In which regions is breast-feeding safer from the impact of toxic elements from the environment?</article-title>
<source>Bosn J Basic Med Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22117830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nassir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Sharify</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baiee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lead and cadmium in the breast milk of lactating mothers living in Hilla City, Babylon, Iraq, during the year 2012</article-title>. <source>Journal of Babylon University</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):np.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Veile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gurven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modernization is associated with intensive breastfeeding patterns in the Bolivian Amazon</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2013.10.034">10.1016/j.socscimed.2013.10.034</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The globalization of cow&#x02019;s milk production and consumption: biocultural perspectives</article-title>. <source>Ecol Food Nutr</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>46</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gurven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jaeggi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Rueden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Does market integration buffer risk, erode traditional sharing practices and increase inequality? A test among Bolivian forager-farmers</article-title>. <source>Hum Ecol</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>530</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liebert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snodgrass</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madimenos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cepon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Implications of market integration for cardiovascular and metabolic health among an indigenous Amazonian Ecuadorian population</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norenzayan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The weirdest people in the world</article-title>? <source>Behav Brain Sci</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2/3</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X0999152X">10.1017/S0140525X0999152X</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20550733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Jasienska</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The Fragile Wisdom: An Evolutionary View on Women&#x02019;s Biology and Health</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jasienska</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energetic factors and seasonal changes in ovarian function in women from rural Poland</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>563</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.20063">10.1002/ajhb.20063</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15368604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colleran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jasienska</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galbarczyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fertility decline and the changing dynamics of wealth, status and inequality</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>, <year>2015</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2015.0287">10.1098/rspb.2015.0287</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25833859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valeggia</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of breastfeeding on anthropometric changes in peri-urban Toba women (Argentina)</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>724</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.10202">10.1002/ajhb.10202</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12953184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breakey</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinde</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valeggia</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sinofsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Illness in breastfeeding infants relates to concentration of lactoferrin and secretory Immunoglobulin A in mother&#x02019;s milk</article-title>. <source>Evol Med Public Health</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/emph/eov002">10.1093/emph/eov002</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25608691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scelza</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Female choice and extra-pair paternity in a traditional human population</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>891</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2011.0478">10.1098/rsbl.2011.0478</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21733870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scelza</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Choosy but not chaste: multiple mating in human females</article-title>. <source>Evol Anthropol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>269</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/evan.21373">10.1002/evan.21373</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24166926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinde</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Field and laboratory methods in human milk research</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.22334">10.1002/ajhb.22334</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23109280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fransson</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000f6;nnerdal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of freezing on distribution of trace elements and minerals in human and cow's milk</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>853</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dorea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Calcium and phosphorus in human milk</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>739</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jarjou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laskey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Randomized, placebo-controlled, calcium supplementation study in pregnant Gambian women: effects on breast-milk calcium concentrations and infant birth weight, growth, and bone mineral accretion in the first year of life</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>83</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>666</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16522914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Calcium secretion into milk</article-title>. <source>J Mammary Gland Biol Neoplasia</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10911-005-5395-z">10.1007/s10911-005-5395-z</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;nnerdal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of mineral and trace elements in human milk: exogenous and endogenous factors</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>58</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1753-4887.2000.tb01869.x">10.1111/j.1753-4887.2000.tb01869.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10946559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stastny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Picciano</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Manganese intake and serum manganese concentration of human milk-fed and formula-fed infants</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1984</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>878</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6539060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hambidge</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Studies in human lactation: secretion of zinc, copper, and manganese in human milk</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>785</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2718914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mastroeni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rond&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Concentrations of Fe, K, Na, Ca, P, Zn and Mg in maternal colostrum and mature milk</article-title>. <source>J Trop Pediatr</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/tropej/fmk004">10.1093/tropej/fmk004</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamawaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kan-no</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yonekubo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Macronutrient, mineral and trace element composition of breast milk from Japanese women</article-title>. <source>J Trace Elem Med Biol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2&#x02013;3</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtemb.2005.05.001">10.1016/j.jtemb.2005.05.001</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16325533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thacher</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pettifor</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okolo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Case-control study of breast milk calcium in mothers of children with and without nutritional rickets</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>826</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/08035250500452613">10.1080/08035250500452613</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fransson</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000f6;nnerdal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution of trace elements and minerals in human and cow&#x02019;s milk</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>915</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1203/00006450-198311000-00015">10.1203/00006450-198311000-00015</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6646903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mello-Neto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rond&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oshiiwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Iron supplementation in pregnancy and breastfeeding and iron, copper and zinc status of lactating women from a human milk bank</article-title>. <source>J Trop Pediatr</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/tropej/fms055">10.1093/tropej/fms055</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23070740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Domell&#x000f6;f</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000f6;nnerdal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>Iron, zinc, and copper concentrations in breast milk are independent of maternal mineral status</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>79</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14684406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Awadi</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srikumar</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>. (2000). <article-title>Trace-element status in milk and plasma of Kuwaiti and non-Kuwaiti lactating mothers</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1069</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1073</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winiarska-Mieczan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cadmium, Lead, Copper and Zinc in Breast Milk in Poland</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>157</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12011-013-9870-x">10.1007/s12011-013-9870-x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24338444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ninh</surname><given-names>NX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isomura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshiike</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hien</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nhug</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Nutritional status of lactating mothers and their breast milk concentration of iron, zinc and copper in rural Vietnam</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Sci Vitaminol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19763035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Calcium, iron and essential fatty acid composition of Bengali mother&#x02019;s milk: a population based cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Indian J Community Health</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gunshin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doudou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trace elements in human milk, cow&#x02019;s milk, and infant formula</article-title>. <source>Agric Biol Chem</source>. <year>1985</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juliao</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RIS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baena</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Concentration profiles of metals in breast milk, drinking water, and soil: relationship between matrices</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12011-014-0030-8">10.1007/s12011-014-0030-8</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24881955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thankachan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurpad</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Breast milk zinc transfer and early post-natal growth among urban South Indian term infants using measures of breast milk volume and breast milk zinc concentrations</article-title>. <source>Matern Child Nutr</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>409</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1740-8709.2012.00421.x">10.1111/j.1740-8709.2012.00421.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22734965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miklav&#x0010d;i&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casetta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tratnik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazej</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krsnik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mariuz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mercury, arsenic and selenium exposure levels in relation to fish consumption in the Mediterranean area</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2012.08.010">10.1016/j.envres.2012.08.010</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in body burden of mercury, lead, arsenic, cadmium and selenium in infants during early lactation in comparison with placental transfer</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2012.07.014">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2012.07.014</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22854743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsiung</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (2013). <article-title>Arsenic, cadmium, lead, and aluminum concentrations in human milk at early stages of lactation</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Neonatol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pedneo.2013.08.005">10.1016/j.pedneo.2013.08.005</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parsaei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nayebpour</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Determination of mercury, cadmium and lead in human milk in Iran</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Ind Health</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>823</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0748233712445047">10.1177/0748233712445047</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22534496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dorea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Iron and copper in human milk</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10705077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>. <article-title>No evidence for sex biases in milk macronutrients, energy, or breastfeeding frequency in a sample of Filipino mothers</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>152</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.22346">10.1002/ajpa.22346</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23996600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feeley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eitenmiller</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Copper, iron, and zinc contents of human milk at early stages of lactation</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6681932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shashiraj</surname></name>, <name><surname>Faridi</surname><given-names>MMA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rusia</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mother&#x02019;s iron status, breastmilk iron and lactoferrin-are they related?</article-title>
<source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>60</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602398">10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602398</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16514410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dorea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Zinc in human milk</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1687</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0271-5317(00)00243-8">10.1016/S0271-5317(00)00243-8</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Zinc in breast milk during prolonged lactation: comparison between the UK and the Gambia</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1990</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2354693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeMaeyer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iyengar</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krikbright</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shoch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Minor and trace elements in human milk from Gautemala, Hungary, Nigeria, Philippines, Sweden, and Zaire</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1711362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>Minor and Trace Elements in Breast Milk: Report of a Joint WHO/IAEA Collaborative Study</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
<year>1989</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Punshon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cottingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Arsenic concentration and speciation in infant formulas and first foods</article-title>. <source>Pure and Applied Chemistry</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>84</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1351/PAC-CON-11-09-17">10.1351/PAC-CON-11-09-17</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22701232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Exposure to arsenic: a major public health concern. 2010. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/ipcs/features/arsenic.pdf">http://www.who.int/ipcs/features/arsenic.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leotsinidis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alexopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kostopoulou-Farri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toxic and essential trace elements in human milk from Greek lactation women: association with dietary habits and other factors</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>61</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>247</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2005.01.084">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2005.01.084</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vouri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x000e4;kinen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuitunen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of dietary intakes of copper, iron, manganese, and zinc on the trace element content of human milk</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1980</year>; <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>231</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7355796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di Rienzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptations to local environments in modern human populations</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>. <year>2014</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gde.2014.06.011">10.1016/j.gde.2014.06.011</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25129844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumssa</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joy</surname><given-names>EMJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ander</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Dietary calcium and zinc deficiency risks are decreasing but remain prevalent</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2014</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/srep10974">10.1038/srep10974</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26098577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Speigelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fawzi</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maternal multiple micronutrient supplementation and pregnancy outcomes in developing countries: meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>89</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2471/BLT.10.083758">10.2471/BLT.10.083758</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zongrone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martorell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of women's nutrition before and during early pregnancy on maternal and infant outcomes: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>S1</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3016.2012.01281.x">10.1111/j.1365-3016.2012.01281.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22742616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaeggi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kortman</surname><given-names>GAM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chassard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holding</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dostal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Iron fortification adversely affects the gut microbiome, increases pathogen abundance and induces intestinal inflammation in Kenyan infants</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>742</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/gutjnl-2014-307720">10.1136/gutjnl-2014-307720</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25143342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>. (1981). <article-title>Long-term energy balance in child-bearing Gambian women</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1981</year>; <volume>34</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2799</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7315781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hinde</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rendina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oftedal</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Daughter dearest: Sex-biased calcium in mother&#x02019;s milk among rhesus macaques</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.22229">10.1002/ajpa.22229</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23446791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>. <source>The place of stunted ironwood trees: A year in the life of the cattle-herding Himba of Namibia</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Continuum International Publishing Group</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chartier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pr&#x000e9;vot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vignaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>The colour of ochres explained by their composition</article-title>. <source>Materials Science and Engineering</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>127</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mseb.2005.09.061">10.1016/j.mseb.2005.09.061</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Molefe O. Physico-chemical characterization of African traditional cosmetics produced by the Ovahimba tribes of Northern Namibia. Dissertation. University of Witwatersrand. 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10539/19285">http://hdl.handle.net/10539/19285</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rifkin</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dayet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Queffelec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lategan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>d&#x02019;Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluating the photoprotective effects of ochre on human skin by in vivo SPF assessment: implications for human evolution, adaptation and dispersal</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0136090</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0136090">10.1371/journal.pone.0136090</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26353012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rifkin</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnographic and experimental perspectives on the efficacy of ochre as a mosquito repellent</article-title>. <source>South Africa Archaeological Bulletin</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>70</volume>(<issue>201</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koletzko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cleghorn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gopalan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Global Standard for the Composition of Infant Formula: Recommendations of an ESPGHAN Coordinated International Expert Group</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1097/01.mpg.0000187817.38836.42">10.1097/01.mpg.0000187817.38836.42</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16254515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gutowska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baranowska-Bosiacka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noce&#x00144;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chlubek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Content of Elements in Infant Formulas and Drinks Against Mineral Requirements of Children</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>158</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>427</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12011-014-9947-1">10.1007/s12011-014-9947-1</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0183367.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mohd-Taufek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hewavitharana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koorts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The Simultaneous Analysis of Eight Essential Trace Elements in Human Milk by ICP-MS</article-title>. <source>Food Anal Methods</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2075</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161-015-0396-z">10.1007/s12161-015-0396-z</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>