<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="rapid-communication"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Curr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Currents</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2157-3999</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20029661</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2770577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="knolid">http://knol.google.com/k/-/-/2te1jx0382flg/4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.RRN1123</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rapid Development of an Efficacious Swine Vaccine for Novel H1N1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vander Veen</surname><given-names>Ryan</given-names></name><!--Research Associate--><xref ref-type="aff">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamrud</surname><given-names>Kurt</given-names></name><!--Scientist--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mogler</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><!--Research Associate--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loynachan</surname><given-names>Alan T.</given-names></name><!--Veterinary pathologist--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McVicker</surname><given-names>Jerry</given-names></name><!--COO--><xref ref-type="aff">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><!--Scientist--><xref ref-type="aff">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>Gary</given-names></name><!--Discovery Scientest--><xref ref-type="aff">**</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><!--Discovery Associate--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Whitney</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff">**</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><!--Chief Scientific Officer--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DL Hank</given-names></name><!--Professor--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x000b6;&#x000b6;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><sup>*</sup>Harrisvaccines, Inc.; <sup>&#x02020;</sup>AlphaVax, Inc; <sup>&#x02021;</sup>Harrisvaccines Inc., Ames, IA; <sup>&#x000a7;</sup>University of Kentucky, Livestock Disease Diagnostic Center; <sup>#</sup>Alphavax Human Vaccines; <sup>**</sup>Alphavax; <sup>&#x02020;&#x02020;</sup>AlphaVax Human Vaccines; <sup>&#x000a7;&#x000a7;</sup>AlphaVax and <sup>&#x000b6;&#x000b6;</sup>Iowa State University</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>RRN1123</elocation-id><history><date date-type="created"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><license><license-p>This research note is distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License.</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p1">Recombinant hemagglutinin (HA) from a novel H1N1 influenza strain was produced using
                an alphavirus replicon expression system. The recombinant HA vaccine was produced
                more rapidly than traditional vaccines, and was evaluated as a swine vaccine
                candidate at different doses in a challenge model utilizing the homologous influenza
                A/California/04/2009 (H1N1) strain. Vaccinated animals showed significantly higher
                specific antibody response, reduced lung lesions and viral shedding, and higher
                average daily gain when compared to non-vaccinated control animals. These data
                demonstrate that the swine vaccine candidate was efficacious at all of the evaluated
                doses.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p2">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;The recent outbreak of pandemic or novel H1N1 in the global human population
                highlights the zoonotic potential of influenza viruses. The current novel H1N1 virus
                has been shown to be of swine origin<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3740210950">[1]</xref>.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Even before this current pandemic, numerous cases of zoonotic
                transmission of swine influenza viruses to humans have been identified.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; A review
                of the literature in 2006 identified 37 civilian cases and 13 military cases of
                human influenza associated with swine influenza strains, spanning from 1958-2005<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-789238949">[2]</xref>.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Fourteen percent&#x000a0;of these cases were documented as fatal.&#x000a0; A more
                recent study reviewed reported cases of triple-reassortant swine influenza subtype
                H1 in humans from 2005-February 2009<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4200946210">[3]</xref>.&#x000a0; They found 11 sporadic cases, and all 11 patients recovered after
                showing clinical influenza symptoms.&#x000a0; Nine of these 11 patients had known exposure
                to pigs, most of which were ill, either at agricultural fairs or at hog farms.&#x000a0;
                These results mirror studies showing increased antibody titers to swine influenza
                viruses among hog farm workers and family members<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1635623084">[4]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3710113505">[5]</xref>.&#x000a0; This demonstrates the role that human and swine interaction can play
                in the creation of novel influenza viruses, and thus the need for efficacious swine
                influenza vaccines.&#x000a0; Currently, novel H1N1 influenza has been detected in swine
                in&#x000a0;several different countries, including Canada, Argentina, Australia, Singapore,
                United Kingdom, Ireland, Norway, and Japan.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1484745119">[6]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3405097026">[7]</xref>.&#x000a0; Recently, the novel H1N1 appeared in the United States in a pig
                exhibited at a fair in Minnesota<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2049069213">[8]</xref>.&#x000a0; Thus, the need for an efficacious novel H1N1 swine vaccine is
                evident.&#x000a0; Novel H1N1 vaccination can reduce clinical disease in pigs, and may reduce
                transmission among the swine population and decrease the zoonotic potential.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p3">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Many vaccines have been evaluated using alphavirus replicon technology (reviewed
                in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2891633452">[9]</xref>).&#x000a0; In this study, the alphavirus replicon is derived from the TC-83
                strain of the alphavirus Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis Virus (VEEV).&#x000a0; In a previous
                study, a VEEV replicon vaccine expressing the HA gene from a human H5N1 isolate
                protected chickens from lethal challenge<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2062135564">[10]</xref>.&#x000a0; Recently, our group became the first to evaluate VEEV replicon
                particle vaccines in swine<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2890121698">[11]</xref>.&#x000a0; However, no studies have been published using replicon-expressed
                recombinant proteins as vaccine candidates for swine.&#x000a0; The objective of this study
                was to evaluate replicon-expressed recombinant novel H1N1 HA protein as a swine
                vaccine in a vaccination-challenge model. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec3"><title>Novel H1N1 HA Replicon Subunit Vaccine Production</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p5">The&#x000a0; Influenza A/California/04/2009 hemagglutinin (HA) nucleotide sequence was
                retrieved from the Global Initiative on Sharing Avian Influenza Data (GISAID)
                database. The gene was synthesized by a commercial company (DNA2.0, Menlo Park, CA,
                USA) with unique AscI and PacI restriction sites engineered at the 5&#x02019; and 3&#x02019; ends,
                respectively.&#x000a0; The HA gene was cloned into the AscI/PacI sites of the pVEK (TC-83)
                replicon vector<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2121263681">[12]</xref> and an optimized construct was selected as previously described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1640956506">[13]</xref>.&#x000a0; The HA gene was then sequenced to ensure the proper sequence was
                maintained through the cloning process.&#x000a0; RNA transcripts were produced <italic>in
                vitro</italic> as previously described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1640956506">[13]</xref>.&#x000a0; Replicon RNA was mixed with Vero cells in electroporation cuvettes
                and pulsed.&#x000a0; Cells were incubated overnight and then lysed using RIPA buffer
                (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA).&#x000a0; Resulting lysate was tested for protein expression by
                Western blot and HA protein concentration was determined by a novel H1N1 HA-specific
                ELISA.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Lysate was diluted to the specified HA concentration and vaccine was
                adjuvanted with Emulsigen-D (MVP Technologies, Omaha, NE, USA).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p7">Vero cell lysate containing recombinant HA protein&#x000a0;was separated by running on a&#x000a0;12%
                SDS-PAGE gel (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and was then transferred to a&#x000a0;PVDF
                membrane (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA).&#x000a0; The&#x000a0; ladder used was the SeeBlue
                Plus2&#x000a0;Pre-Stained Standard (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA).&#x000a0;After transfer, membrane
                was blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk at room temperature.&#x000a0; Membrane was incubated
                with swine polyclonal anti-novel H1N1 HA for two hours, washed three times, followed
                by incubation with goat anti-swine IgG horseradish peroxidase conjugate
                (ImmunoJackson Research Laboratories, Inc, West Grove, PA, USA) for one hour, and
                washed three times.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Detection was performed&#x000a0;using TMB substrate (KPL, Gaithersburg,
                MD, USA).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Direct Antigen Capture ELISA</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p9">Unknown samples, negative controls,&#x000a0; and purified novel H1 protein (Protein Sciences,
                Meriden, CT, USA) were directly captured to NUNC Maxisorp (Rochester, NY, USA)
                96-well microplates by diluting with capture buffer (50 mM Carbonate/Bicarbonate, pH
                9.6) and incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C (100 &#x000b5;l/well).&#x000a0; The microplates were washed four
                times with wash buffer (20 mM Phosphate Buffered Saline, 0.05% Tween-20, pH 7.2).&#x000a0;
                The plates were blocked with 1.25% non-fat dry milk in capture buffer for 1 hour at
                37&#x000b0;C (200 &#x000b5;l/well).&#x000a0; After four washes, pig polyclonal anti-novel H1N1 HA was added
                to wells (100 &#x000b5;l) and incubated for 1 hour at 37&#x000b0;C (diluted 1/500 in wash buffer
                containing 1.25% NFDM).&#x000a0; Following four washes, goat ant-pig IgG-HRP labeled
                (Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA, USA) was added to the wells (100 &#x000b5;l) and
                incubated for 1 hour at 37&#x000b0;C (diluted 1/2000 in was buffer containing 1.25% NFDM).&#x000a0;
                Four final washes were performed prior to the addition of 100 &#x000b5;l of TMB substrate
                (KPL, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) and incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 20 minutes.&#x000a0; Absorbance
                values were measured at 620 nm and a standard curve was plotted with the purified
                novel H1 protein.&#x000a0; Linear regression analysis of the standard curve was used to
                calculate the novel H1 concentrations in the unknowns.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Animal Studies</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p11">Pigs free of swine influenza virus (SIV) and porcine reproductive and respiratory
                syndrome virus (PRRSV) were obtained at three weeks of age.&#x000a0; Pigs were randomized
                and separated into 4 groups of 5 pigs each (table 1).&#x000a0; Prior to vaccination, serum
                was collected and tested by the homologous hemagglutination inhibition (HI) assay
                against the novel H1N1 A/California/04/2009 strain to confirm negative antibody
                status.&#x000a0; Sera were collected throughout the study and tested by this same HI assay
                to monitor seroconversion post-vaccination.&#x000a0; A prime/boost vaccination schedule was
                followed.&#x000a0; The first dose of vaccine was given to pigs at approximately 4 weeks of
                age on day 0.&#x000a0; On day 21 pigs received booster vaccination, with challenge on day 47
                and necropsy on day 52.&#x000a0; Pigs received either phosphate buffered saline (PBS)
                (Placebo, Group 1) or different concentrations of novel H1 HA recombinant protein
                (Groups 2-4, Table 1).&#x000a0; Pigs were challenged intratracheally with virulent
                A/California/04/2009 (CDC# 2009712047) at a dose of 2x10<sup>5</sup>
                TCID<sub>50</sub>/ml.&#x000a0; Nasal swabs were collected daily for live virus isolation
                beginning on day of challenge and continuing until study completion 5 days
                post-challenge.&#x000a0; Pigs were weighed immediately before challenge and again at
                necropsy for determination of average daily gain (ADG).&#x000a0; At necropsy, gross lung
                lesion consolidation was determined by a board-certified pathologist.&#x000a0; Lung tissue
                was fixed in formalin for SIV immunohistochemistry (IHC) and histopathological
                analysis.&#x000a0; Bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) was collected from lungs for live
                virus isolation.&#x000a0; This animal study was approved by the Iowa State University
                Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Hemaglutination Inhibition Assay</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p13">Antibodies to influenza virus were measured by HI assay run by the University of
                Minnesota Veterinary Diagnostic Laboratory following standard laboratory protocol.
                Briefly, sera were treated with receptor-destroying enzyme, heat inactivated,
                adsorbed with 20% turkey erythrocytes, and centrifuged. Supernatants were then
                serially diluted in V-shaped well microtiter plates with an equal volume containing
                4-8 agglutinating units of A/California/04/2009 and plates were incubated at room
                temperature before addition of 0.5% turkey erythrocytes.&#x000a0; Titer was defined as the
                reciprocal of the maximal dilution at which hemagglutination was inhibited.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Gross Lung Lesion Scoring, Histopathology, and SIV Immunohistochemistry</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p15">A single board-certified veterinary pathologist who was blinded to group treatments,
                performed gross lung scoring, histopathological analysis, and SIV
                Immunohistochemistry (IHC) analysis.&#x000a0; At necropsy, each lung lobe affected by
                pneumonia was visually estimated, and a total percentage for the entire lung was
                calculated based on weighted proportions of each lobe to the total lung volume<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1501057364">[14]</xref>.&#x000a0; Tissue samples from the trachea and all lung lobes were collected
                and fixed in 10% formalin.&#x000a0; Tissues were routinely processed and stained with
                hematoxylin and eosin.&#x000a0; Lung samples were scored according to the method used by
                Vincent et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3803711290">[15]</xref>. Swine influenza virus IHC was done according to the method described
                by Vincent et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3276089922">[16]</xref>.&#x000a0; All tissue preparation and staining was done by the Iowa State
                University Veterinary Diagnostic Laboratory.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Live Virus Isolation</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p17">Live virus titers were determined from nasal swabs and live virus isolation performed
                on BALF samples.&#x000a0; Briefly, nasal swabs and BALF samples were thawed and centrifuged
                to remove cellular debris.&#x000a0; The resulting supernatant was diluted 10-fold in 96 well
                plates in Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) (Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA)
                containing 1% antibiotic-antimycotic (Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and 1% L-glutamine
                (Mediatech, Manassas, VA, USA).&#x000a0; After dilutions were made, 100&#x000b5;l was transferred
                from each well into respective wells of a 96 well plate which contained a monolayer
                of swine testicle (ST) cells.&#x000a0; Plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C until no further CPE
                was observed, typically 3-5 days.&#x000a0; Wells displaying CPE were considered positive,
                and titers were calculated using the TCID<sub>50</sub>/ml method of Reed-Meunch<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2787179564">[17]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p19">Single factor analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to analyze homologous HI titers,
                macroscopic and histopathological lung scores, IHC and BALF results, log10
                transformed nasal swab viral titers, and ADG (JMP 8.0.1, SAS Institute Inc., Cary,
                NC, USA). &#x000a0;Statistical significance was set at p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><title>Vaccine Preparation</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p21">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;The novel H1N1 HA gene was inserted into the alphavirus replicon platform
                according to the methods listed previously.&#x000a0; Nucleotide sequencing after insertion
                confirmed the correct HA gene sequence had been maintained throughout the cloning
                process.&#x000a0; Western blotting performed on protein lysate confirmed expression of the
                novel HA protein at all the varying HA doses (Figure 1) used in vaccine preparation
                for the animal study. The HA concentration was determined by novel HA ELISA and
                diluted to the specified HA concentration (Table 1).&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p23">Figure 1: Western blot confirming recombinant HA&#x000a0; expression.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p24">
                <fig id="d20e272"><graphic xlink:href="hs04-lysate-dilutions-good-09302009"/></fig>
            </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p26">Lane 1: Ladder</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p27">Lane 2: Vero lysate (negative control)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p28">Lane 3: Recombinant HA (28.5&#x000b5;g/ml)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p29">Lane 4: Recombinant HA (1.14&#x000b5;g/ml)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p30">Lane 5: Recombinant HA (0.57&#x000b5;g/ml)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p31">Lane 6: Recombinant HA (0.38&#x000b5;g/ml)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p44">Table 1: Design of novel H1N1 recombinant HA vaccine study.&#x000a0; Pigs received
                either&#x000a0;placebo vaccine (PBS, Group 1) or varying doses of HA antigen (Groups 2-4).&#x000a0;
                All vaccines were given intramuscularly as 2ml doses on days 0 and 21.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p45">
                <table-wrap id="d20e321"><table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="383"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:57pt">Group</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:99pt">Vaccine</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:131pt">HA concentration/dose</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:57pt">1</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:99pt">Sham</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:131pt">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:57pt">2</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:99pt">Recombinant HA </td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:131pt">1.14&#x000b5;g</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:57pt">3</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:99pt">Recombinant HA </td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:131pt">0.57&#x000b5;g</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:57pt">4</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:99pt">Recombinant HA </td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:131pt">0.38&#x000b5;g</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
            </p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>Antibody&#x000a0;Titers&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; </title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p62">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Post-vaccination sera were tested for specific antibody response by the
                homologous HI assay.&#x000a0; Hemagglutination inhibition titers were not seen in vaccinated
                pigs after one dose, but were all positive (&#x02265;1:40), except for a single pig in Group
                2, at 7 and 14 days post-boost vaccination (data not shown).&#x000a0; On the day of
                challenge, homologous HI titers were significantly higher in Groups 2-4 when
                compared to Group 1 (Table 2).&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p64">Table 2.&#x000a0; Summary of hemagglutination inhibition (HI) titers, average macroscopic and
                microscopic lung involvement, immunohistochemistry (IHC), and average daily gain
                (ADG).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p65">
                <table-wrap id="d20e387"><table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="577"><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:48pt">Group</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">HI Titers<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">% Pneumonia<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">HistopathologicScore<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">Lung IHC<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">ADG<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:48pt">1</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">&#x0003c;10</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">15.6 &#x000b1; 5.4</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1.8 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">5/5</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1.76 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:48pt">2</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">121*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1.4 &#x000b1; 0.9*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">0.8 &#x000b1; 0.2*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1/5*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">2.56 &#x000b1; 0.68</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:48pt">3</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">184*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">0.2 &#x000b1; 0.2*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">0.6 &#x000b1; 0.2*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">0/5*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">2.64 &#x000b1; 0.22*</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:48pt">4</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">106*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1.8 &#x000b1; 1.1*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">0.8 &#x000b1; 0.2*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">1/5*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77pt">2.45 &#x000b1; 0.34*</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
            </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p96"><sup>a</sup>Geometric mean homologous HI titers</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p97"><sup>b</sup>Group mean &#x000b1; standard error</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p98"><sup>c</sup>0-3, group mean &#x000b1; standard error</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p99"><sup>d</sup>Number of positive samples per group</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p100"><sup>e</sup>ADG post-challenge in pounds, group mean &#x000b1; standard error</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p101">*Values are significantly different from non-vaccinates (Group 1) within a column at
                p &#x0003c; 0.05</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec14"><title>Pathological Evaluation</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p103">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;At necropsy, lungs exhibited macroscopic dark purplish-red consolidated lesions
                located mainly in the cranioventral lobes.&#x000a0; Lungs taken from Groups 2-4 exhibited
                significantly lower lesion scores and consolidation than pigs in Group 1 (Table 2).&#x000a0;
                There was also a significant reduction in pathological scores in all vaccinated
                groups compared to the non-vaccinated group (Table 2).&#x000a0; The lung sections taken from
                non-vaccinated Group 1 pigs had approximately 50% of the airways affected by
                bronchiolar epithelial disruption and peribronchiolar lymphocytic cuffing.&#x000a0; The
                vaccinated Groups 2-4 demonstrated only occasional affected airways with light
                cuffing.&#x000a0; Swine influenza virus IHC was also performed on lung sections. All 5 lungs
                taken from non-vaccinated Group 1 pigs were positive for influenza antigen, while
                only 2 pigs in total from the vaccinated Groups 2-4 were positive.&#x000a0; &#x000a0;Additionally,
                SIV IHC was done on trachea samples taken from each pig at necropsy (data not
                shown).&#x000a0; Although there were positive trachea IHC samples in all groups, there was
                no significant differences between vaccinated and non-vaccinated groups.&#x000a0; Positive
                trachea IHC results correlate with what was previously reported on pathogenesis of
                novel H1N1 in ferrets<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1002982521">[18]</xref>.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>Average Daily Gain</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p105">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;All pigs were weighed on the day of challenge and again at necropsy.&#x000a0; Groups 3
                and 4 had significantly higher ADG over the 5 day period following challenge than
                did Group 1 (Table 2).&#x000a0; Group 2 did exhibit higher ADG but was not significantly
                higher than Group 1 (p=0.08).&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>Virus Isolation</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p107">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;No live influenza virus was detected one day post-challenge from nasal swabs
                (Table 3).&#x000a0; On day 2 post challenge live influenza virus was detected in Groups 1,
                3, and 4, although there were no significant differences between mean group viral
                titers.&#x000a0; On day 3 post-challenge Groups 2 and 4 had significantly lower titers than
                did Group 1.&#x000a0; On both days 4 and 5 Groups 2-4 all exhibited lower titers than Group
                1.&#x000a0; No live virus was detected in nasal swabs from any pigs in Group 2 for the
                duration of the challenge period.&#x000a0; Similarly, there was a significant reduction in
                the number of positive BALF samples between groups (Table 3).&#x000a0; By 5 days post-
                challenge, only a total of 3 vaccinated pigs had detectable live virus in BALF
                samples, while all 5 pigs in the non-vaccinated group were virus isolation positive.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p109">Table 3. Summary of live virus isolation from nasal swabs and bronchoalveolar lavage
                fluid(BALF).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p110">
                <table-wrap id="d20e550"><table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="612"><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">&#x000a0;</td><td valign="bottom" colspan="5" rowspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:345.05pt">Nasal Swab<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">BAL<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">Group</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:52.75pt">1 DPC<sup>c</sup>
                                </td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:65.9pt">2 DPC</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:70.5pt">3 DPC</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">4 DPC</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">5 DPC</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">5 DPC</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">1</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:52.75pt">0</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:65.9pt">0.85 &#x000b1; 0.53</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:70.5pt">2.55 &#x000b1; 0.66</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">3.05 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">3.05 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">2</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:52.75pt">0</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:65.9pt">0</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:70.5pt">0*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">0*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">0*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">2/5*</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">3</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:52.75pt">0</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:65.9pt">1.05 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:70.5pt">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.65</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">0.9 &#x000b1; 0.57*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.62*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">0/5*</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:47pt">4</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:52.75pt">0</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:65.9pt">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.45</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:70.5pt">0.5 &#x000b1; 0.5*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.65*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:77.95pt">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.65*</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1" style="background-color:transparent;width:67pt">1/5*</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
            </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p149"><sup>a</sup>Log<sub>10</sub> mean virus titers &#x000b1; standard error in nasal swabs
                post-challenge</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p150"><sup>b</sup>Number of positive BALF samples per group</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p151"><sup>c</sup>Days post-challenge (DPC)</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p152">* Values are significantly different from non-vaccinates (Group 1) within a column at
                p &#x0003c; 0.05</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec></sec><sec id="sec17"><title>Discussion</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p154">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;The recent outbreak of novel H1N1 in the human population has highlighted the
                zoonotic potential that influenza viruses possess.&#x000a0; Even before the current
                pandemic, there were many reported cases of swine to human transmission of
                influenza.&#x000a0; As such, part of controlling this zoonotic threat is vaccination of
                swine against swine influenza viruses.&#x000a0; In this study, we demonstrate how rapidly an
                efficacious swine influenza vaccine based on the alphavirus replicon expression
                system can be produced in response to an outbreak of a novel zoonotic strain.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p155">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;This study&#x000a0;deomnstrated the quickness and flexibility with which a vaccine can
                be produced using the alphavirus replicon expression system.&#x000a0; It took less than two
                months from the time the novel HA sequence was retrieved from GISAID database until
                pigs were administered the first vaccine dose.&#x000a0; Traditional methods for producing
                influenza vaccines take much longer and are dependent on viral replication in
                embryonated eggs or on tissue culture cells with subsequent inactivation.&#x000a0; In the
                face of an influenza epidemic, a quick turnaround is important in preventing further
                transmission and decreasing the zoonotic potential.&#x000a0; The alphavirus replicon
                platform allows for rapid insertion of any influenza HA (or other) gene, making it
                an attractive influenza vaccine technology due to constant antigenic shift and drift
                among influenza viruses.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p156">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;This is the first report of immunization of swine with a recombinant protein
                produced via an alphavirus replicon expression system.&#x000a0; Replicon particle (RP)
                vaccines produced with this system have recently been utilized to induce protection
                against swine influenza virus (SIV) and porcine reproductive and respiratory
                syndrome virus (PRRSV) in swine<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2890121698">[11]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1361391363">[19]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-184477080">[20]</xref>.&#x000a0; The first proof of concept study demonstrated that a replicon
                particle vaccine administered to swine was able to induce high antibody HI titers
                against a human influenza strain. A subsequent study using an RP vaccine expressing
                the HA gene of a clade IV H3N2 SIV isolate confirmed that influenza HA RP vaccines
                given to swine are not only able to induce an antibody response, but also provide
                significant protection against a homologous viral challenge.&#x000a0; In contrast to these
                earlier studies, this study used an alphavirus replicon expression system to produce
                recombinant HA protein<italic> in vitro</italic>; however, similar antibody response and
                protection from viral challenge was demonstrated. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p157">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;The results demonstrate that influenza infection in swine with
                A/California/04/2009 is able to induce clinical symptoms and gross lesions
                comparable to other strains of SIV<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3803711290">[15]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1445159275">[21]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2785736750">[22]</xref>. In contrast with a previous study, several pigs (primarily in the
                non-vaccinated group) in this study exhibited clinical signs, mainly coughing and
                sneezing.&#x000a0; This discrepancy may be due to the miniature pig model used in
                the&#x000a0;previous study<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-772926556">[23]</xref>.&#x000a0; In this study, vaccine administration induced specific antibody
                titers, reduced macroscopic and histopathologic lung lesions, and reduced viral load
                in both the nose and lung.&#x000a0; Vaccinated pigs also demonstrated a higher average daily
                gain than non-vaccinates. These results demonstrate that this recombinant novel HA
                protein is efficacious when used as a vaccine against novel H1N1 swine influenza.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p158">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;To date, novel H1N1 has been confirmed to exist in swine in several countries,
                including the United States<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1484745119">[6]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3405097026">[7]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2049069213">[8]</xref>.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Several recent studies have already reported the successful
                transmission of novel H1N1 virus from infected to na&#x000ef;ve contact &#x000a0;pigs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2598463077">[24]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3761053113">[25]</xref>.&#x000a0; The successful transmission of this virus among pigs and recent
                confirmation of its' presence in the United States demonstrates the need for an
                efficacious novel H1N1 vaccine.&#x000a0; This paper shows that vaccination of pigs against
                novel H1N1 can&#x000a0;reduce both clinical symptoms and virus shedding&#x000a0;in pigs, which may
                lead to decreased transmission.</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Acknowledgements</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p159">The authors wish to thank Drs. Matthew Erdman and&#x000a0;J. Dustin&#x000a0;Loy for critical
                    reading of this manuscript.&#x000a0; Thanks also to Brandon Russell for his assistance,
                    and to the&#x000a0;Iowa State University&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;University of Minnesota&#x000a0;Veterinary
                    Diagnostic Labs, including Al Ducommun and Ling Tong.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec19"><title>Funding Information</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p161">&#x000a0;This work was supported by the Grow Iowa Values Fund.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec20"><title>Competing Interests</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p164">Harris is the founder and president of Harrisvaccines, Inc.&#x000a0; Vander Veen, Mogler,
                    and McVicker are employees of Harrisvaccines, Inc.&#x000a0; Kamrud, Berglund, Owens,
                    Timberlake, Lewis, and Smith are employees of AlphaVax.&#x000a0; Alphavax provided the
                    novel H1N1 HA replicon vector and Harrisvaccines, Inc. provided the vaccine used
                    in this study.&#x000a0; Neither Harrisvaccines, Inc.&#x000a0;nor AlphaVax have patents
                    associated with this replicon.&#x000a0; Harrisvaccines, Inc. is submitting documents to
                    the USDA in support of conditional licensure for the vaccine. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref-3740210950"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garten RJ, Davis CT, Russell CA, Shu B, Lindstrom
            S, Balish A, Sessions WM, Xu&#x0000d; X, Skepner E, Deyde V, Okomo-Adhiambo M, Gubareva
            L, Barnes J, Smith CB, Emery&#x0000d; SL, Hillman MJ, Rivailler P, Smagala J, de Graaf
            M, Burke DF, Fouchier RA, Pappas&#x0000d; C, Alpuche-Aranda CM, L&#x000f3;pez-Gatell H, Olivera
            H, L&#x000f3;pez I, Myers CA, Faix D, Blair&#x0000d; PJ, Yu C, Keene KM, Dotson PD Jr, Boxrud D,
            Sambol AR, Abid SH, St George K,&#x0000d; Bannerman T, Moore AL, Stringer DJ, Blevins P,
            Demmler-Harrison GJ, Ginsberg M,&#x0000d; Kriner P, Waterman S, Smole S, Guevara HF,
            Belongia EA, Clark PA, Beatrice ST,&#x0000d; Donis R, Katz J, Finelli L, Bridges CB,
            Shaw M, Jernigan DB, Uyeki TM, Smith DJ, &#x0000d; Klimov AI, Cox NJ. Antigenic and
            genetic characteristics of swine-origin 2009&#x0000d; A(H1N1) influenza viruses
            circulating in humans. Science. 2009 Jul&#x0000d; 10;325(5937):197-201. Epub 2009 May
            22. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19465683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-789238949"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Myers KP, Olsen CW, Gray GC. Cases of swine
            influenza in humans: a review of&#x0000d; the literature. Clin Infect Dis. 2007 Apr
            15;44(8):1084-8. Epub 2007 Mar 6.&#x0000d; Review. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17366454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1973337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4200946210"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shinde V, Bridges CB, Uyeki TM, Shu B, Balish A, Xu
            X, Lindstrom S, Gubareva&#x0000d; LV, Deyde V, Garten RJ, Harris M, Gerber S, Vagasky S,
            Smith F, Pascoe N, Martin &#x0000d; K, Dufficy D, Ritger K, Conover C, Quinlisk P,
            Klimov A, Bresee JS, Finelli L.&#x0000d; Triple-reassortant swine influenza A (H1) in
            humans in the United States,&#x0000d; 2005-2009. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jun
            18;360(25):2616-25. Epub 2009 May 7. Erratum&#x0000d; in: N Engl J Med. 2009 Jul
            2;361(1):102. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1635623084"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Olsen CW, Brammer L, Easterday BC, Arden N, Belay
            E, Baker I, Cox NJ.&#x0000d; Serologic evidence of H1 swine Influenza virus infection in
            swine farm residents &#x0000d; and employees. Emerg Infect Dis. 2002 Aug;8(8):814-9. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12141967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2732505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3710113505"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gray GC, McCarthy T, Capuano AW, Setterquist SF,
            Olsen CW, Alavanja MC. Swine &#x0000d; workers and swine influenza virus infections.
            Emerg Infect Dis. 2007&#x0000d; Dec;13(12):1871-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1484745119"><mixed-citation>ProMED-mail. Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009, Animal health (08):
            Singapore, Swine. ProMED-mail; 04 Sept: 20090904.3114. www.promedmail.org. 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3405097026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">OIE World Animal Health Information Database. Vol
            22 Nos. 18-43. April 30-October 22, 2009.
            http://www.oie.int/wahis/public.php?page=weekly_report_index&#x00026;admin=0. 2009. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2049069213"><mixed-citation>United States Department of Agriculture press release No. 0514.09.
            USDA Confirms 2009 Pandemic H1N1 Influenza Sample Present in Minnesota Fair Pig Sample.
                10/19/2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2891633452"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rayner JO, Dryga SA, Kamrud KI. Alphavirus vectors
            and vaccination. Rev Med&#x0000d; Virol. 2002 Sep-Oct;12(5):279-96. Review. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12211042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2062135564"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schultz-Cherry S, Dybing JK, Davis NL, Williamson
            C, Suarez DL, Johnston R,&#x0000d; Perdue ML. Influenza virus (A/HK/156/97)
            hemagglutinin expressed by an alphavirus&#x0000d; replicon system protects chickens
            against lethal infection with Hong Kong-origin &#x0000d; H5N1 viruses. Virology. 2000
            Dec 5;278(1):55-9. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11112481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2890121698"><mixed-citation>Erdman MM, Kamrud KI, Harris DL, Smith J. Alphavirus Vector
            Vaccines Developed for Use in Humans Induce High Levels of Antibodies to Influenza Virus
            Hemagglutinin in Swine: Proof of Concept. Vaccine (manuscript accepted). 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2121263681"><mixed-citation>Hooper JW, Ferro AM, Golden JW, Sivera P, Dudek J, Alterson K,
            Custer M, Rivers B, Morris J, Owens G, Smith JF, Kamrud KI. Molecular Smallpox Vaccine
            Delivered by Alphavirus Replicons Elicits Protective Immunity in Mice and Non-human
            Primates. Vaccine (manuscript accepted). 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1640956506"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kamrud KI, Custer M, Dudek JM, Owens G, Alterson
            KD, Lee JS, Groebner JL,&#x0000d; Smith JF. Alphavirus replicon approach to promoterless
            analysis of IRES elements.&#x0000d; Virology. 2007 Apr 10;360(2):376-87. Epub 2006 Dec
            6. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17156813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1885372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1501057364"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Halbur PG, Paul PS, Frey ML, Landgraf J, Eernisse K,
            Meng XJ, Lum MA, Andrews &#x0000d; JJ, Rathje JA. Comparison of the pathogenicity of two
            US porcine reproductive and&#x0000d; respiratory syndrome virus isolates with that of
            the Lelystad virus. Vet Pathol. &#x0000d; 1995 Nov;32(6):648-60. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8592800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3803711290"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vincent AL, Ma W, Lager KM, Janke BH, Webby RJ,
            Garc&#x000ed;a-Sastre A, Richt JA.&#x0000d; Efficacy of intranasal administration of a truncated
            NS1 modified live influenza &#x0000d; virus vaccine in swine. Vaccine. 2007 Nov
            19;25(47):7999-8009. Epub 2007 Sep 29. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2099695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3276089922"><mixed-citation>Vincent LL, Janke BH, Paul PS, Halbur PG. Demonstration of swine
            influenza virus in formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissues by use of an
            immunohistochemical test. Proceedings of the 14th IPVS Congress. 1996;97.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2787179564"><mixed-citation>Reed LJ and Muench H. A simple method of estimation of 50% end
            points. American journal of Hygiene. 27;493-497. 1938.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1002982521"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Munster VJ, de Wit E, van den Brand JM, Herfst S,
            Schrauwen EJ, Bestebroer TM,&#x0000d; van de Vijver D, Boucher CA, Koopmans M,
            Rimmelzwaan GF, Kuiken T, Osterhaus AD, &#x0000d; Fouchier RA. Pathogenesis and
            transmission of swine-origin 2009 A(H1N1) influenza&#x0000d; virus in ferrets. Science.
            2009 Jul 24;325(5939):481-3. Epub 2009 Jul 2. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19574348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1361391363"><mixed-citation>Ermdan MM, Kamrud KI, Smith J, Harris DL. Vaccination of pigs with
            alphavirus replicon particles expressing ORFs 5 and 6 from porcine reproductive and
            respiratory syndrome virus reduces viremia after challenge. Vaccine (manuscript
            submitted). 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-184477080"><mixed-citation>Bosworth B, Erdman M, Stine D, Harris I, Irwin C, Jens M, Loynachan
            A, Owens G, Kamrud K, Harris DL. Viral replicon particle vaccine protects pigs against
            influenza. Veterinary Therapeutics (manuscript submitted). 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1445159275"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vincent AL, Lager KM, Ma W, Lekcharoensuk P, Gramer
            MR, Loiacono C, Richt JA. &#x0000d; Evaluation of hemagglutinin subtype 1 swine
            influenza viruses from the United&#x0000d; States. Vet Microbiol. 2006 Dec
            20;118(3-4):212-22. Epub 2006 Aug 1. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16962262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2785736750"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sreta D, Kedkovid R, Tuamsang S, Kitikoon P,
            Thanawongnuwech R. Pathogenesis&#x0000d; of swine influenza virus (Thai isolates) in
            weanling pigs: an experimental trial.&#x0000d; Virol J. 2009 Mar 25;6:34. PubMed Central PMCID:&#x0000d; PMC2678088. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19317918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2678088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-772926556"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Itoh Y, Shinya K, Kiso M, Watanabe T, Sakoda Y,
            Hatta M, Muramoto Y, Tamura D,&#x0000d; Sakai-Tagawa Y, Noda T, Sakabe S, Imai M, Hatta
            Y, Watanabe S, Li C, Yamada S,&#x0000d; Fujii K, Murakami S, Imai H, Kakugawa S, Ito M,
            Takano R, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K,&#x0000d; Shimojima M, Horimoto T, Goto H, Takahashi K,
            Makino A, Ishigaki H, Nakayama M,&#x0000d; Okamatsu M, Takahashi K, Warshauer D, Shult
            PA, Saito R, Suzuki H, Furuta Y,&#x0000d; Yamashita M, Mitamura K, Nakano K, Nakamura M,
            Brockman-Schneider R, Mitamura H, &#x0000d; Yamazaki M, Sugaya N, Suresh M, Ozawa M,
            Neumann G, Gern J, Kida H, Ogasawara K, &#x0000d; Kawaoka Y. In vitro and in vivo
            characterization of new swine-origin H1N1&#x0000d; influenza viruses. Nature. 2009 Aug
            20;460(7258):1021-5. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19672242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2748827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2598463077"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brookes SM, Irvine RM, Nunez A, Clifford D, Essen
            S, Brown IH, Van Reeth K,&#x0000d; Kuntz-Simon G, Loeffen W, Foni E, Larsen L,
            Matrosovich M, Bublot M, Maldonado J,&#x0000d; Beer M, Cattoli G. Influenza A (H1N1)
            infection in pigs. Vet Rec. 2009 Jun&#x0000d; 13;164(24):760-1. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3761053113"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lange E, Kalthoff D, Blohm U, Teifke JP, Breithaupt
            A, Maresch C, Starick E,&#x0000d; Fereidouni S, Hoffmann B, Mettenleiter TC, Beer M,
            Vahlenkamp TW. Pathogenesis&#x0000d; and transmission of the novel swine-origin
            influenza virus A/H1N1 after&#x0000d; experimental infection of pigs. J Gen Virol. 2009
            Sep;90(Pt 9):2119-23. Epub 2009&#x0000d; Jul 10. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19592456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>