<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="rapid-communication"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Curr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Currents</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2157-3999</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20029669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2781303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="knolid">http://knol.google.com/k/-/-/1dfgb8wq76hv/3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="accession">RRN1132</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.RRN1132</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>H1N1 vaccination and adults with underlying health conditions in the US</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name><!--Research Scientist--><xref ref-type="aff">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><!--Professor of Epidemiology--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><sup>*</sup>Harvard School of Public Health and <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Dept of Epidemiology and Center for Communicable Disease Dynamics, Harvard School of Public Health</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>RRN1132</elocation-id><history><date date-type="created"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><license><license-p>This research note is distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License.</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p1">65% of fatalities from pH1N1 infections in a large US case series occur in adults with underlying health conditions other than pregnancy, but it appears that only relatively few high-risk adults will get vaccinated during the fall wave of pH1N1 transmission.  There are several reasons for this problem; the most important is vaccine shortage.  High risk adults (other than pregnant women) were not part of the initial, narrow priority cohort which included pregnant women and children ages 0.5-4; this is despite the fact that some of those high risk groups, such as adults with immunosuppressive conditions and possibly individuals with neurological disorders, have a relative risk for fatality (per capita) higher than pregnant women, and over 28-fold higher than healthy children under the age of 4. With more vaccine becoming available than needed in the initial priority cohort, a broader group which includes high risk adults and individuals under 24 becomes eligible for vaccine in many locations.  Nonetheless, due to continuing high demand, high-risk adults face competition for vaccine from healthy individuals under 24; additionally, some locations specifically prioritize school students over high-risk adults. Finally, there is an issue of awareness and a shortage of specific channels that target high risk adults other than pregnant women and facilitate vaccine distribution among them in the US.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p2">A recent CDC estimatesuggests that death toll from H1N1 is larger than previously thought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3138676241">[1]</xref>, approximately 4000 deaths from April to October 2009. In a recent case series<bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref></bold>, over 65% of fatalities among hospitalized H1N1 patients were adults with underlying health conditions other than pregnancy. &#x000a0;&#x000a0;A previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2627144473">[3]</xref>, with a higher proportion of children among the hospitalized patients than <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref>, found that 72% of hospitalized adults had an underlying condition other than pregnancy.&#x000a0;Among individuals who died or were admitted to ICU in the same study, 67% had an underlying health condition. Other studies&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2020325050">[4]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-72253294">[5]</xref> have found a high percentage of individuals with underlying medical conditions among the H1N1 related fatalities. In children about 70-80% of fatalities involved underlying conditions&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2935900243">[6]</xref> (particularly neurological disorders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3086158399">[7]</xref>).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p3">With limited information on H1N1 fatalities stratified by age and underlying conditions, we attempt to assess the relative risks of some high risk group for which data is available. Our data sources are <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2248779010">[8]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4207029303">[9]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3989531823">[10]</xref>. Also throughout this paper, a relative risk for death for a high-risk group is the ratio of the death rate (per capita) in this high-risk group over the death rate in the whole population.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p4">Pregnant women constitute 1% of the US population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2248779010">[8]</xref>. The proportion of pregnant women among deaths in&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref> is 5.1%. Thus an estimate of the relative risk for pH1N1 death for pregnant women in the US is 5.1.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p5">Morbidly obese adults (BMI &#x02265; 40) constitute 4.8% of the adult US population and correspondingly 3.63% of the of the whole US population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3989531823">[10]</xref>. &#x000a0;Data in&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref> suggest that morbidly obese adults constitute 31.5% of fatal cases. Thus, the relative risk for death for morbidly obese adults may be estimated as 8.7.&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p6">Data on the prevalence of immunosuppressing conditions have been assembled by the MIDAS High Risk Segmentation Group&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4207029303">[9]</xref> from the 2006 National Health Interview Survey, the CDC HIV/AIDS surveillance 2007 report, the US Renal Data System, and the Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network, and kindly provided by Diane Wagener.&#x000a0; Immunocompromised adults represent 1.9% of the US population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4207029303">[9]</xref>.&#x000a0;They represent 30.5% of all fatalities in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref>. Immunocompromised adults thus have an estimated 16-fold higher risk of death than the general population.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p7">We have no data on prevalence of individuals with neurological (neurocognitive and neuromuscular) disorders, but adults with neuromuscular disorders represent 11.9% of all deaths in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref>.&#x000a0; People with neurocognitive or neuromuscular disorders each represent 13.4% of deaths or ICU admissions in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2627144473">[3]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p8">Children aged 0.5-4 (6-59 months) without underlying conditions make up about 6% of the US population. We have no data on their share among the H1N1-related fatalities. Children under 18 make up 13.9% of fatalities in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3138676241">[1]</xref>, and 6.8% of fatalities in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref>. The number from&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3138676241">[1]</xref> may be an overestimate as it makes certain assumptions on ascertainment of fatalities in children and adults; nonetheless we assume it to estimate children&#x02019;s share among the fatalities.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2935900243">[6]</xref> suggests that only 20-30% of fatalities in children involve no major underlying conditions; the number in&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref> is 2/8. We assume that 25% of fatalities in children involve no major underlying conditions. Finally we need to know the share of those aged 0.5-4 among the fatalities in healthy children. Even if we assume it is 100%, the relative risk for fatality of healthy children aged 0.5-4 (compared to the whole US population) is estimated as at most 0.58 (25% x 13.9%/6%); the estimated risk for adults with immunosuppressive conditions is 28 times that of healthy children aged 0.5-4. If we assume that at most half of all fatalities in healthy children occur in those aged 0.5-4, the relative risk for adults with immunosuppressive conditions compared to healthy children aged 0.5-4 becomes 56.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p9">We want to point out that unlike the case of fatalities, children have the highest rates for H1N1-relatedhospitalizations (http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/recs/acip/downloads/mtg-slides-oct09/12-2-flu-vac.pdf); moreover among children, the percentage of those not having major underlying conditions is higher for hospitalizations than for fatalities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1192054440">[2]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2627144473">[3]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2935900243">[6]</xref>. The high percentage of children among the hospitalizations, together with the perception that among all groups in the general population, children merit the most protection(http://www.flu.gov/individualfamily/vaccination/allocationguidance.pdf) were some of the reasons behind the high prioritization that healthy children received in the US.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p10"><bold>Vaccine distribution to high-risk adults: </bold>Despite high relative risks for certain groups of adults with underlying health conditions, it appears that only a few of them will get immunized in time to be protected against the fall wave of H1N1 infections in the US.&#x000a0; With demand for vaccines exceeding supply, a number of jurisdictions, at least initially, have restricted vaccine distribution to a priority cohort that does not include high risk adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1255934384">[11]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3061913652">[12]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1092964782">[13]</xref>. The ACIP&#x02019;s <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/rr58e0821a1.htm">recommended </ext-link>&#x0201c;Subset of Target Groups During Limited Vaccine Availability&#x0201d; includes pregnant women, caregivers for infants less than 6 months, health care workers at direct infection risk, children 6 months to 4 years, and high-risk children 5-18, but not high-risk adults. While we disagree with the choice to exclude high-risk adults from this &#x0201c;Subset of Target Groups,&#x0201d; we do not advocate changing it at this time. However, many jurisdictions are beginning to expand vaccination beyond this Subset, and more will do so as vaccine supplies grow.&#x000a0; In some locations, this expansion involves prioritizing school-age children over high-risk adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2289477279">[14]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1335155590">[15]</xref> a choice that does not maximize the use of the vaccine to prevent fatal outcomes.&#x000a0; Evidently a more common strategy is to offer vaccine to a broader group that includes high risk adults and all individuals under 24 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3818914640">[16]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1518635246">[17]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-738869599">[18]</xref>. Inevitably, this creates competition for still-limited vaccine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3708889441">[19]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p11">One possible way to resolve the discrepancy above is creation of a channel which will specifically target high-risk adults, increasing both their awareness and vaccination levels. For instance in the UK, GPs contact their priority patients and offer them vaccine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3986692423">[20]</xref>; also in the UK, people with underlying conditions are prioritized over children under 5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1460496613">[21]</xref>. A similar strategy of health care providers focusing on patients with underlying conditions is being pursued in Oregon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-596592747">[22]</xref>. An alternative suggestion is to offer vaccines specifically for high risk individuals, perhaps opening clinics in large adult ambulatory care practices or in other settings where high-risk adults are likely to be present.&#x000a0; Such clinics might limit their offerings to individuals with high risk conditions, similar to campaigns in schools that are limited to school-age children <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1489504186">[23]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2289477279">[14]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-340964204">[24]</xref>. As public health messaging expands beyond the initial &#x0201c;Subset of Target Groups,&#x0201d; we urge that special emphasis be placed on adults in documented high-risk groups, in an effort to maximize the impact of remaining vaccine delivery on pH1N1 mortality.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p12"><bold>Acknowledgment:</bold> The MIDAS High Risk Segmentation Group (D. Wagener, R. Zimmerman, D. Lauderdale) kindly shared the data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4207029303">[9]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p13"><bold>Funding Information:</bold>  This work was funded by the US National Institutes of Health Models of Infectious Disease Agent Study Cooperative Agreements 5U01GM076497 and 1U54GM088588 to ML for the Harvard Center for Communicable Disease Dynamics (ML,EG).</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p14"><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> ML has consulted for the Avian/Pandemic Flu Registry (Outcome Sciences), funded in part by Roche, and for Novartis Vaccines and Diagnostics.&#x000a0; EG declares no competing interests.</p></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref-3138676241"><mixed-citation>CDC Estimates of 2009 H1N1 Influenza Cases, Hospitalizations and Deaths in the United States, April &#x02013; October 17, 2009<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/h1n1flu/estimates_2009_h1n1.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/h1n1flu/estimates_2009_h1n1.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1192054440"><mixed-citation>Janice K. Louie; Meileen Acosta; Kathleen Winter; et al. Factors associated with death or hospitalization due to pandemic 2009 influenza A(H1N1) infection in California. JAMA. 2009;302(17):1896-1902<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi:10.1001/jama.2009.1583">http://doi:10.1001/jama.2009.1583</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2627144473"><mixed-citation>Jain S, Kamimoto L, Bramley AM, Schmitz AM, Benoit SR, Louie J, et al. Hospitalized Patients with 2009 H1N1 Influenza in the United States, April-June 2009. N Engl J Med 2009 Oct 8.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/NEJMoa0906695">http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/NEJMoa0906695</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2020325050"><mixed-citation>Ministerio de Salud, Chile. Influenza pandemica (H1N1) 2009. REPORTE 21 DE OCTUBRE DE<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.redsalud.gov.cl/minsalaudios/reporte22octubre.pdf">http://www.redsalud.gov.cl/minsalaudios/reporte22octubre.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-72253294"><mixed-citation>Perez-Padilla R, de la Rosa-Zamboni D, Ponce de Leon S, Hernandez M, Quinones-Falconi F, Bautista E, et al. Pneumonia and respiratory failure from swine-origin influenza A (H1N1) in Mexico. N Engl J Med2009 Aug 13;361(7):680-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2935900243"><mixed-citation>H1N1 leading to increased flu rates, more pediatric deaths<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rwjf.org/publichealth/digest.jsp?id=23828">http://www.rwjf.org/publichealth/digest.jsp?id=23828</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3086158399"><mixed-citation>Swine flu poses risks to kids with neurological conditions. Medline Plus, Sep. 3, 2009<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/news/fullstory_88952.html">http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/news/fullstory_88952.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2248779010"><mixed-citation>Jamieson DJ, Honein MA, Rasmussen SA, Williams JL, Swerdlow DL, Biggerstaff MS, et al. H1N1 2009 influenza virus infection during pregnancy in the USA. Lancet. 2009 Aug 8;374(9688):451-8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4207029303"><mixed-citation>MIDAS High Risk Segmentation Group. (D. Wagener, private communication, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3989531823"><mixed-citation>Ogden CL, Carroll MD, Curtin LR, McDowell MA, Tabak CJ, Flegal KM. Prevalence of overweight and obesity in the United States, 1999-2004. JAMA. 2006; 295(13):1549-1555.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1255934384"><mixed-citation>Albany, NY vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wnyt.com/article/stories/S1253179.shtml?cat=300">http://wnyt.com/article/stories/S1253179.shtml?cat=300</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3061913652"><mixed-citation>Texas vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bccourier.com/Archives/News_detail.php?recordID=091112N7">http://www.bccourier.com/Archives/News_detail.php?recordID=091112N7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1092964782"><mixed-citation>Minnesota vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reviewmessenger.com/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=3366:h1n1-vaccination-clinic-set-for-high-risk-groups&#x00026;catid=35:other-local-news">http://www.reviewmessenger.com/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=3366:h1n1-vaccination-clinic-set-for-high-risk-groups&#x00026;catid=35:other-local-news</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2289477279"><mixed-citation>Hawaii vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/20091114/NEWS15/911140323/LOCALNEWSFRONT/Moanalua+Middle+gets+swine+flu+shots">http://www.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/20091114/NEWS15/911140323/LOCALNEWSFRONT/Moanalua+Middle+gets+swine+flu+shots</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1335155590"><mixed-citation>Central Ohio vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.nbc4i.com/cmh/news/local/article/central_ohios_h1n1_vaccine_clinics/25276/">http://www2.nbc4i.com/cmh/news/local/article/central_ohios_h1n1_vaccine_clinics/25276/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3818914640"><mixed-citation>Wyoming vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thetimes-tribune.com/news/health_and_science/clinics_set_for_h1n1_shots">http://www.thetimes-tribune.com/news/health_and_science/clinics_set_for_h1n1_shots</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1518635246"><mixed-citation>Alabama vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.oanow.com/oan/news/local/article/h1n1_vaccination_clinic_set_for_tuesday/109199/">http://www2.oanow.com/oan/news/local/article/h1n1_vaccination_clinic_set_for_tuesday/109199/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-738869599"><mixed-citation>Arizona vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yumasun.com/news/yuma-54207-county-clinic.html">http://www.yumasun.com/news/yuma-54207-county-clinic.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3708889441"><mixed-citation>New York long lines<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gothamist.com/2009/11/14/long_lines_for_swine_flu_vaccine_at.php">http://gothamist.com/2009/11/14/long_lines_for_swine_flu_vaccine_at.php</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3986692423"><mixed-citation>The Scottish Government. Influenza H1N1 &#x02013; who will be vaccinated.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Health/health/AvianInfluenza/mexicanswiuneflu/mexicanswinefluQandA/vaccination/who">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Health/health/AvianInfluenza/mexicanswiuneflu/mexicanswinefluQandA/vaccination/who</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1460496613"><mixed-citation>HPA, November 19, 2009. Extension of the swine flu vaccination programme.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publichealth/Flu/Swineflu/InformationandGuidance/Vaccinationprogramme/DH_108850">http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publichealth/Flu/Swineflu/InformationandGuidance/Vaccinationprogramme/DH_108850</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-596592747"><mixed-citation>Oregon vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mailtribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20091114/NEWS/911140310">http://www.mailtribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20091114/NEWS/911140310</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1489504186"><mixed-citation>South Carolina vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.heraldonline.com/front/story/1744749.html">http://www.heraldonline.com/front/story/1744749.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-340964204"><mixed-citation>NY schools vaccination<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wcax.com/Global/story.asp?S=11508539">http://www.wcax.com/Global/story.asp?S=11508539</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>