<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="rapid-communication"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Curr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Currents</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2157-3999</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20029607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2762375</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="knolid">http://knol.google.com/k/-/-/1y43omtho1mv6/3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="accession">RRN1013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.RRN1013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mortality and morbidity burden associated with A/H1N1pdm influenza virus</article-title><subtitle>Who is likely to be infected, experience clinical symptoms, or die from the H1N1pdm 2009 pandemic virus ?</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><!--Research Director, Physician, Scientist, Captain, United States Public Health Service--><xref ref-type="aff">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Viboud</surname><given-names>Cecile</given-names></name><!--Scientist (Mathematical Epidemiology), US National Institutes of Health--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>Lone</given-names></name><!--Research Professor--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>Donald R.</given-names></name><!--Research Director ISDS, Historical Epidemiologist--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>Colin</given-names></name><!--Scientist, Epidemiologist, Evolutionary Biologist--><xref ref-type="aff">&#x000b6;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><sup>*</sup>National Institutes of Health; <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Fogarty International Center, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA; <sup>&#x02021;</sup>Department of Global Health, George Washington University, School of Public Health and Health Services, DC; <sup>&#x000a7;</sup>International Society for Disease Surveillace and <sup>&#x000b6;</sup>University of Cambridge &#x00026; Fogarty International Center - NIH</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>RRN1013</elocation-id><history><date date-type="created"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><license><license-p>This research note is distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License.</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p1">Here we use lessons from past influenza pandemics and recent information about the H1N1pdm pandemic to discuss variations in H1N1pdm disease burden with age, underlying risk factors, and geography.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p2">Influenza is predominantly caused by influenza viruses type A and B which continuously circulate amongst humans throughout the world.&#x000a0; In temperate climates, influenza seasons occur typically during the late fall to late winter with peak periods during the winter.&#x000a0; In tropical and sub-tropical regions, influenza viruses circulate year round with less seasonal activity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2432799907">[1]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-997541243">[2]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2966156964">[3]</xref> </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><sec id="sec1"><title>Influenza viruses during epidemics and&#x000a0; pandemics</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p4">Type A influenza viruses are further classified by sub-type based on the viral surface antigens, the hemaglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase&#x000a0;(NA). Antibodies to the HA are considered protective against infection, while those against NA reduce disease severity.&#x000a0; There are 16 known sub-types of HA circulating in birds, the natural reservoir of&#x000a0;influenza viruses; only three, thus far, are known to result in <bold>continuous</bold> transmission amongst humans (viruses containing hemaglutinin subtype 1 A(H1), subtype 2 A(H2) and subtype 3 A(H3)).&#x000a0;&#x000a0; (While Type B viruses also infect humans, illnesses are typically less severe and none are known to have caused true pandemics).&#x000a0; The eight gene segments of the different viruses which infect birds and mammals&#x000a0;can reassort and sometimes&#x000a0;create viruses with a&#x000a0;new&#x000a0;HA, which can transmit among&#x000a0;humans, who have very little immunity&#x000a0;-- resulting in&#x000a0;a <bold>pandemic</bold>.&#x000a0; Over the last 91 years, four of these reassortant or HA <bold>shift</bold> in viruses have resulted in successful human-to-human&#x000a0;transmission&#x000a0;and caused pandemics (A(H1) in 1918, A(H2) in 1957, A(H3) in 1968, A(H1pdm) in 2009. In the 1957 and 1968 pandemics, the&#x000a0;novel&#x000a0;influenza&#x000a0;virus&#x000a0;replaced the previously circulating subtype (this also presumably occurred in 1918 based on antigenic studies, though it cannot be stated definitively as there has been no human influenza virus isolated from before 1918).&#x000a0; In 1977 when A(H1) viruses re-emerged virtually unchanged after a 20-year absence, they did not become dominant, as measured by the majority of isolates recovered from ill individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2461074647">[4]</xref>, but instead co-circulated with the A(H3) viruses.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p5">The emerging A(H1pdm) virus of &#x000a0;2009 may or may not replace the previously circulating A(H1) and A(H3) viruses.&#x000a0;As of Aug 2009, seasonal A(H1) and A(H3) viruses continue to circulate along with A(H1pdm), although generally at lower levels than usual <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2676382397">[5]</xref>.</p><sec id="sec3"><title>Prior immunity to influenza viruses in 2009</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p6">For almost all persons born from 1918 to 1957 (~52 to 91 year olds in 2009), the&#x000a0;first exposure to an influenza A virus was to the strains containing A(H1); those born from 1957 to 1968 (~41 to ~52) to&#x000a0; A(H2); those born since the last pandemic in 1968 (&#x0003c;41 years of age), most likely to A(H3).&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Indeed, the A(H1) subtype has been reintroduced in 1977 but is&#x000a0;rarely dominant [5],&#x000a0; suggesting that most people born after 1977&#x000a0;were first exposed&#x000a0;to A(H3) viruses.&#x000a0;This is important because the concept of &#x0201c;original antigenic sin&#x0201d; postulates that the virus sub-type that one is first exposed to in childhood will provide the greatest immunity in later years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1417885054">[6]</xref>&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1651572119">[7]</xref>.&#x000a0; Therefore, those persons born prior to 1957 may have the greatest natural&#x000a0;immunity to the currently circulating&#x000a0; A(H1pdm) pandemic virus&#x000a0; in 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2689651998">[8]</xref>.&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p7">These age groups provide a rough guide as to who was infected with each virus sub-type as not all individuals may have been infected in childhood at the time of emergence of pandemic viruses.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; </p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Influenza infection and transmission</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p8">Influenza viruses are highly transmissible person to person through the respiratory route with a reproduction number ranging between 1.1 and 1.8 and a serial interval of 2-3 days&#x000a0; during seasonal epidemics, meaning that each case infects 1.1 to 1.8 other individuals every 2-3 days on average<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2712381966">[9]</xref>.&#x000a0; Transmission amongst individuals is believed to&#x000a0;vary with&#x000a0;multiple factors including age, population density, contact rates, climatological conditions and immunity profiles within populations.&#x000a0; Children have the highest contact rates and can accelerate local transmission, while adults are known to spread the virus over greater distances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2586113832">[10]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2516851896">[11]</xref>&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4290985627">[12]</xref>. An estimated 5 to 20% of the world&#x02019;s population become infected during each seasonal epidemic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-66195449">[13]</xref>.&#x000a0; It has been reported that up to 50% of Infants with siblings become infected during an influenza season.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4213909383">[14]</xref></p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p9">During pandemic seasons,&#x000a0;as a greater proportion of the population is susceptible, transmission is higher, with an estimated&#x000a0;R=1.5-5.5 secondary cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2626515033">[15]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-449499248">[16]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1753871717">[17]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-242060706">[18]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-620091492">[19]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3178550312">[20]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2363587834">[21]</xref> especially in younger populations, and a larger fraction of the population experiences clinical symptoms, estimated at around 30% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-26843612">[22]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2468589493">[23]</xref>.&#x000a0; One study documented 85% of children to be infected in Cleveland during the first year of the 1957 pandemic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-26843612">[22]</xref>. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p10">The new sub-type virus may circulate for several years although it will mutate or will genetically <bold>drift</bold> over that time and continue to cause epidemics until replaced with a new pandemic virus. Hence, with each new shift of a new influenza virus, with a high initial year attack rate and an annual seasonal attack rate on the order of 5 to 20% everyone will eventually become infected with the new pandemic strain over several years. This may occur in several waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-201415366">[24]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p12">While most influenza epidemiology studies were set in developed countries, evidence from the Gambia shows over 90% seroconversion with multiple infections of the A(H3) pandemic virus within 4 years of the 1968 pandemic.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1812614655">[25]</xref>&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Signature Features of Pandemics</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p14">As older individuals may have been previously exposed to&#x000a0;previously circulating influenza&#x000a0;virus subtypes during their childhood, the mortality and morbidity burden of a pandemic shifts to a younger population with most infections and mortality occurring during the earliest phases of the pandemic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-49572071">[26]</xref>&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1663586838">[27]</xref>.&#x000a0;Aside from the shift of the dominant circulating viral sub-type and in the age patterns of deaths and illnesses,&#x000a0; rapid transmission due to the greater susceptibility in the general population, there are other signature features of pandemics, including multiple waves of morbidity and mortality over the first few months or years, and disruption from the typical winter seasonality observed in seasonal epidemics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-201415366">[24]</xref>. There is also great variation of pandemic health burden amongst populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-281760855">[28]</xref>,&#x000a0; although the impact of influenza remains poorly studied in developing country populations. In the most severe reported 1918-20 pandemic, mortality was estimated to range from 0.2% in Scandinavian countries to nearly 8% in some regions in India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-281760855">[28]</xref>, a difference&#x000a0; of ~40 fold.&#x000a0; Of note, there may be issues of ascertainment bias from historical data, and these mortality&#x000a0;rates are not directly applicable to the current H1N1pdm outbreak as circulating viruses, populations, and treatment capabilities have dramatically changed since 1918.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Illness and death from seasonal and pandemic influenza</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p17">While it is expected that 100% of the population to be eventually infected with the new pandemic virus, the virulence and pathogenicity of the&#x000a0;virus is related to multiple factors, many of which are somewhat independent of infectivity.&#x000a0; While influenza viruses may be highly infectious, they may not necessarily cause much disease burden in the general population. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p18">Other viral factors may contribute to severity of influenza-related infection, including virulence factors in HA, NS1 and PB1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4066684272">[29]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-486622969">[30]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2095877729">[31]</xref>.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Virulence is also dependent on various host factors; some well established or hypothesized such as co-morbid conditions, obesity, pregnancy, pneuomococcal carriage, host genomics, and perhaps protection from prior exposure to sub-type virus in childhood &#x000a0;(i.e. those born prior to 1957).&#x000a0;  </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Relevance to the current H1N1pdm pandemic </title><sec id="sec10"><title>Impact of the first A/H1N1pdm pandemic wave, Apr-Aug 2009.</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p25">Since April 2009, most countries have reported laboratory-confirmed cases of H1N1pdm.&#x000a0; It is also clear that these counts would greatly underestimate the total burden of the first pandemic wave, as most cases would not have been confirmed.&#x000a0; For example, CDC had discouraged physicians from laboratory testing due to overwhelmed laboratory system a few weeks into the outbreak. &#x000a0;Consequently, the count of ~100K cases in late July was known to be severely undercounted; instead, CDC estimated that over 1M persons had been infected in the US.&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p26">The 1<sup>st</sup> wave of H1N1pdm in summer 2009 can be characterized as mild, relative to the mortality impact of severe winter-seasonal influenza epidemics.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;However the H1N1pdm outbreak&#x000a0;is associated with the &#x0201c;signature age shift&#x0201d; that is typical for influenza pandmics.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Morbidity and mortality&#x000a0;have tended to occur in adults aged 20-50 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2689651998">[8]</xref>, with some deaths in children, and largely sparing of seniors.&#x000a0; Both of these features &#x02013; a mild summer wave with elevated mortality in young adults resembles the pattern of the 1918 pandemic, in which a first spring wave in the US &#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3782600159">[32]</xref> or summer wave&#x000a0;in Europe&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-36843574">[33]</xref> was associated with unusual deaths in young adults.&#x000a0; The subsequent catastrophic wave in autumn 1918 killed about 2% of the population world-wide, with a dramatic mortality elevation&#x000a0;in young adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-281760855">[28]</xref>.&#x000a0;Of note, the 1<sup>st</sup> wave of the H1N1pdm virus has had a very different morbidity impact in various US cities and regions, something that cannot easily be explained by contemporary mathematical models.&#x000a0; For example, about 7% of persons living in NY City are thought to have been infected this summer, while other cities did not see much of an elevation in influenza illness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1079708010">[34]</xref>.&#x000a0; Similarly, while Argentina has been experiencing an emergency situation, surrounding countries like New Zealand have had far less of an impact <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3872237679">[35]</xref>.&#x000a0; Such variability of impact have previously been noted for 1918-20 pandemic&#x000a0;&#x000a0;and attributed to differences in access to care and overall risk of dying in developing countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1663586838">[27</xref>].</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p28">The early phases of recognition of emerging infections almost always show a high case fatality rate due to the dramatic ascertainment of cases and the unknown extent of infections that have already occurred.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Media and public health alarm bells are frequently sounded until there is a clearer understanding of the degree of background infections are measured as well as transmission rates.&#x000a0; Limited laboratory diagnostic tests and uncertain definitions of disease during the early phase lead to frequent misunderstandings. With improved sensitive and specific diagnostics and population based surveys, a clearer picture emerges.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p30">The uncertainly about the&#x000a0;number of people infected (=denominator&#x000a0;for case fatality rate) is critical when it comes to ascertaining the case fatality ratio and thus getting a stronger sense of the severity of this pandemic.&#x000a0; It is extremely difficult to gauge how many people have been infected thus far, based on passive surveillance data available, which consists mostly of deaths, hospitalizations,&#x000a0;or influenza-like-illnesses. The proportion of symptomatic cases who seek care and are captured by existing surveillance systems remains unclear is is bound to vary across countries and settings, and&#x000a0;with media addition as the pandemic progresses.&#x000a0;So far, estimates of the case fatality rate range between 1 per 10,000 for Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrom (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4081367586">[36]</xref>) to 1 per 2,000 for all influenza-related deaths. These estimates come with large cofnidence intervals and are likely to change over time. Of note, the case fatality rate for seasonal influenza is 1 per 1,000 on average, which appears more severe than H1N1pdm, however one has to remembers that it is mostly driven by a high proportion of deaths among seniors. By contrast,&#x000a0;H1N1pdm-related deaths are concentrated in people under 60 yrs, a population&#x000a0;typically at low risk of influenza-related deaths.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p32">In addition, an&#x000a0;important quantity to gauge disease severity is the proportion of asymptomatic cases, which remains largely&#x000a0;unknown (for H1N1pdm as well as for seasonal influenza viruses). The proportion of asymptomatic cases&#x000a0;can only be measured by costly prospective studies combining serological outcomes&#x000a0;to measure&#x000a0;evidence of infection, with a clinical follow-up of patients to monitor symptoms. Such studies&#x000a0;were conducted in the 1940-1970s in US and British households and&#x000a0;proved&#x000a0;&#x000a0;instrumental in monitoring the impact of past pandemics (eg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-26843612">[22]</xref>).&#x000a0;So far, there has not&#x000a0;been&#x000a0;such studies for H1N1pdm,&#x000a0;although some may be under way. </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p34">&#x000a0;In the meantime, to monitor trends in H1N1pdm burden over time or across age groups, we can rely on existing passive surveillance systems which&#x000a0;are insensitive to the ascertainment issues &#x02013; for example, CDCs 122 mortality system, which&#x000a0;showed only a moderate elevation of mortality during the 1<sup>st</sup> wave in summer in the US&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1924325024">[37]</xref>.&#x000a0; Thus, at least in the US, it is clear that the 1<sup>st</sup> wave was not associated with a measurable amount of excess mortality above the seasonal baseline.&#x000a0; This is not to say that severe outcomes and deaths have not occurred; CDCs pediatric surveillance system shows that influenza related hospitalizations and deaths occurred nationwide; however, the numbers were definitely lower than that attributed to seasonal influenza during the last 4 influenza seasons. &#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p36">&#x000a0;But some other countries have reported&#x000a0;high hospitalization&#x000a0;impact.&#x000a0; For example, in the Southern hemisphere where the influenza season is normally during May-September, the impact has been reported to be &#x0201c;the worst in the last decade&#x0201d; in New Zealand and Argentina, with ICUs filled.&#x000a0; &#x000a0;But also the UK had an intense first wave, despite&#x000a0;high use of antivirals for prophylaxis and treatment.&#x000a0; In Mexico, adults aged 20-50 had a clearly elevated hospitalization rate than for a comparison period in previous years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2689651998">[8]</xref>.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p38">Clearly, more data are urgently needed to assess the mortality and morbidity burden of the first wave of&#x000a0;H1N1pdm, and&#x000a0; quantify variation across countries and age groups.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>What will happen in the 2nd wave expected this autumn?</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p40">Even though the similarities of the epidemiology of H1N1pdm and the 1918 pandemic&#x000a0;are concerning, there is no way of knowing whether the current H1N1pdm virus will cause a more severe 2<sup>nd</sup> wave in the coming fall.&#x000a0; The virus may or may not acquire virulence mutations and become a more pathogenic state in successive waves.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p42">There are some unique differences in this pandemic from prior pandemics.&#x000a0; As noted earlier, A(H1) viruses have previously circulated in the population, and may have conferred&#x000a0; some level of protection to&#x000a0;older age groups, who&#x000a0;are relatively spared against morbidity and mortality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2689651998">[8]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-366374342">[38]</xref></p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p43">&#x000a0;Evolution dictates that success of transmission and ability to compete with other evolving viruses will determine the characteristics of&#x000a0;future strains.&#x000a0; There have been historic examples of mild, moderate or severe waves followed&#x000a0;in previous pandemics&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-201415366">[24]</xref>. However, even if this pandemic is at the mild end of scale,&#x000a0;it is worth keeping in mind the age shift of severe disease to younger populations, warranting increased attention to populations not normally thought about at greater risk.&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p44">While there is no way to predict the course of this pandemic, careful statistical measurements of age-specific morbidty and mortality data, combined&#x000a0;with information&#x000a0;on virus activity and genetic characteritics, allows for an assessment of pandemic impact,&#x000a0;and is crucial&#x000a0;in&#x000a0;the first two years&#x000a0;of a new virus circulation&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3920945608">[39]</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-49572071">[26]</xref>. </p></sec></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>Factors that may affect H1N1pdm impact in the waves to come</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p45">On the positive side, some factors could attenuate the mortality impact of&#x000a0;subsequent waves of H1N1pdm, possibly in the&#x000a0;fal, in particular effective pandemic vaccination.&#x000a0;In addition,&#x000a0;immunity acquired&#x000a0;from exposure to H1N1pdm in summer 2009&#x000a0;could protect a fraction of the population against subsequent outbreaks of&#x000a0;similar or related&#x000a0;viruses in fall&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3750324927">[40]</xref>. Other factors include antiviral and antibiotic use&#x000a0;(to mitigate primary viral infection and&#x000a0;secondary bacterial infections),&#x000a0;school closings, and effective social mitigation strategies.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p46">On the negative side, other factors could lead to a worsening situation in the coming months.&#x000a0;&#x000a0; These include winter-seasonal factors in the Northern Hemisphere, including presence of bacterial pathogens such as S.pneumo and MRSA, who are responsible for a large fraction of influenza-triggered deaths in&#x000a0; seasonal epidemics and past pandemics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1355644555">[41]</xref>. &#x000a0;As discussed previously, viral acquisition of virulence factors by mutation would be unfortunate, as would acquisition of antiviral resistance determinants.&#x000a0; </p><!--WRITE-PARA--><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Acknowledgments</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p49">We thank Marc Lipsitch and Derek Smith&#x000a0;for helpful discussions.</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec19"><title>Funding information</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p51">The study was funded by the&#x000a0;intra-mural program of the Fogarty International Center, National Institutes of Health.&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</p><!--WRITE-PARA--></sec><sec id="sec20"><title>Competing interests</title><!--WRITE-PARA--><p id="p53">The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref-2432799907"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alonso WJ, Viboud C, Simonsen L, Hirano EW, Daufenbach LZ, Miller MA.&#x0000d;
Seasonality of influenza in Brazil: a traveling wave from the Amazon to the&#x0000d;
subtropics. Am J Epidemiol. 2007 Jun 15;165(12):1434-42. Epub 2007 Mar 16. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-997541243"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Viboud C, Alonso WJ, Simonsen L. Influenza in tropical regions. PLoS Med. 2006&#x0000d;
Apr;3(4):e89. Epub 2006 Mar 7. PubMed Central PMCID:&#x0000d;
PMC1391975. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16509764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1391975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2966156964"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russell CA, Jones TC, Barr IG, Cox NJ, Garten RJ, Gregory V, Gust ID, Hampson &#x0000d;
AW, Hay AJ, Hurt AC, de Jong JC, Kelso A, Klimov AI, Kageyama T, Komadina N,&#x0000d;
Lapedes AS, Lin YP, Mosterin A, Obuchi M, Odagiri T, Osterhaus AD, Rimmelzwaan&#x0000d;
GF, Shaw MW, Skepner E, Stohr K, Tashiro M, Fouchier RA, Smith DJ. The global&#x0000d;
circulation of seasonal influenza A (H3N2) viruses. Science. 2008 Apr&#x0000d;
18;320(5874):340-6. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2461074647"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Simonsen L, Reichert TA, Viboud C, Blackwelder WC, Taylor RJ, Miller MA.&#x0000d;
Impact of influenza vaccination on seasonal mortality in the US elderly&#x0000d;
population. Arch Intern Med. 2005 Feb 14;165(3):265-72. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15710788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2676382397"><mixed-citation>Australian Surveillance System<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.gov.au/internet/main/publishing.nsf/Content/cda-surveil-ozflu-flucurr.htm">http://www.health.gov.au/internet/main/publishing.nsf/Content/cda-surveil-ozflu-flucurr.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1417885054"><mixed-citation>Thomas Francis, Jr. (Dec. 15, 1960). "On the doctrine of original antigenic sin." Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society 104(6): 572&#x02013;578.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1651572119"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dowdle WR. Influenza pandemic periodicity, virus recycling, and the art of&#x0000d;
risk assessment. Emerg Infect Dis. 2006 Jan;12(1):34-9. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2689651998"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chowell G, Bertozzi SM, Colchero MA, Lopez-Gatell H, Alpuche-Aranda C,&#x0000d;
Hernandez M, Miller MA. Severe respiratory disease concurrent with the&#x0000d;
circulation of H1N1 influenza. N Engl J Med. 2009 Aug 13;361(7):674-9. Epub 2009 &#x0000d;
Jun 29. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2712381966"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chowell G, Miller MA, Viboud C. Seasonal influenza in the United States,&#x0000d;
France, and Australia: transmission and prospects for control. Epidemiol Infect. &#x0000d;
2008 Jun;136(6):852-64. Epub 2007 Jul 18. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2680121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2586113832"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brownstein JS, Kleinman KP, Mandl KD. Identifying pediatric age groups for&#x0000d;
influenza vaccination using a real-time regional surveillance system. Am J&#x0000d;
Epidemiol. 2005 Oct 1;162(7):686-93. Epub 2005 Aug 17. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16107568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1266301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2516851896"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Viboud C, Bj&#x000f8;rnstad ON, Smith DL, Simonsen L, Miller MA, Grenfell BT.&#x0000d;
Synchrony, waves, and spatial hierarchies in the spread of influenza. Science.&#x0000d;
2006 Apr 21;312(5772):447-51. Epub 2006 Mar 30. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16574822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4290985627"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wallinga J, Teunis P, Kretzschmar M. Using data on social contacts to estimate&#x0000d;
age-specific transmission parameters for respiratory-spread infectious agents. Am&#x0000d;
J Epidemiol. 2006 Nov 15;164(10):936-44. Epub 2006 Sep 12. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-66195449"><mixed-citation>Noble GR. Epidemiological and clinical aspects of influenza. In: Beare AS, ed. Basic and applied influenza research. Boca Raton, Florida: CRC Press, 1982:11&#x02013;50.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4213909383"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Glezen WP, Taber LH, Frank AL, Gruber WC, Piedra PA. Influenza virus&#x0000d;
infections in infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1997 Nov;16(11):1065-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9384341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2626515033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fraser C, Donnelly CA, Cauchemez S, Hanage WP, Van Kerkhove MD, Hollingsworth &#x0000d;
TD, Griffin J, Baggaley RF, Jenkins HE, Lyons EJ, Jombart T, Hinsley WR, Grassly &#x0000d;
NC, Balloux F, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Rambaut A, Pybus OG, Lopez-Gatell H,&#x0000d;
Alpuche-Aranda CM, Chapela IB, Zavala EP, Guevara DM, Checchi F, Garcia E,&#x0000d;
Hugonnet S, Roth C; WHO Rapid Pandemic Assessment Collaboration. Pandemic&#x0000d;
potential of a strain of influenza A (H1N1): early findings. Science. 2009 Jun&#x0000d;
19;324(5934):1557-61. Epub 2009 May 11. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19433588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-449499248"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Longini IM Jr, Nizam A, Xu S, Ungchusak K, Hanshaoworakul W, Cummings DA,&#x0000d;
Halloran ME. Containing pandemic influenza at the source. Science. 2005 Aug&#x0000d;
12;309(5737):1083-7. Epub 2005 Aug 3. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1753871717"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chowell G, Bettencourt LM, Johnson N, Alonso WJ, Viboud C. The 1918-1919&#x0000d;
influenza pandemic in England and Wales: spatial patterns in transmissibility and&#x0000d;
mortality impact. Proc Biol Sci. 2008 Mar 7;275(1634):501-9. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18156123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2596813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-242060706"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chowell G, Nishiura H, Bettencourt LM. Comparative estimation of the&#x0000d;
reproduction number for pandemic influenza from daily case notification data. J R&#x0000d;
Soc Interface. 2007 Feb 22;4(12):155-66. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17254982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2358966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-620091492"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chowell G, Ammon CE, Hengartner NW, Hyman JM. Estimation of the reproductive&#x0000d;
number of the Spanish flu epidemic in Geneva, Switzerland. Vaccine. 2006 Nov&#x0000d;
10;24(44-46):6747-50. Epub 2006 Jun 5. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3178550312"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andreasen V, Viboud C, Simonsen L. Epidemiologic characterization of the 1918 &#x0000d;
influenza pandemic summer wave in Copenhagen: implications for pandemic control&#x0000d;
strategies. J Infect Dis. 2008 Jan 15;197(2):270-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2674012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2363587834"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mills CE, Robins JM, Lipsitch M. Transmissibility of 1918 pandemic influenza. &#x0000d;
Nature. 2004 Dec 16;432(7019):904-6. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15602562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26843612"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">JORDAN WS Jr, DENNY FW Jr, BADGER GF, CURTISS C, DINGLE JH, OSEASOHN R,&#x0000d;
STEVENS DA. A study of illness in a group of Cleveland families. XVII. The&#x0000d;
occurrence of Asian influenza. Am J Hyg. 1958 Sep;68(2):190-212. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13571232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2468589493"><mixed-citation>Frost WH (1920) Statistics of Influenza Morbidity, with Special Reference to Certain Factors in Case Incidence and Case Fatality. Washington: Government Printing Office.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-201415366"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Miller MA, Viboud C, Balinska M, Simonsen L. The signature features of&#x0000d;
influenza pandemics--implications for policy. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jun&#x0000d;
18;360(25):2595-8. Epub 2009 May 7. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1812614655"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schild GC, Newman RW, McGregor IA, Williams K. The use of transportable
single-radial-diffusion immunoplates in seroepidemiological studies of influenza 
in the Gambia. The occurrence and persistence of antibody to influenza A/Hong
Kong/68 (H3N2) virus in selected inhabitants of two rural villages. Bull World
Health Organ. 1977;55(1):3-13. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">408021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2366616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49572071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Simonsen L, Clarke MJ, Schonberger LB, Arden NH, Cox NJ, Fukuda K. Pandemic&#x0000d;
versus epidemic influenza mortality: a pattern of changing age distribution. J&#x0000d;
Infect Dis. 1998 Jul;178(1):53-60. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9652423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1663586838"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Epstein SL. Prior H1N1 influenza infection and susceptibility of Cleveland&#x0000d;
Family Study participants during the H2N2 pandemic of 1957: an experiment of&#x0000d;
nature. J Infect Dis. 2006 Jan 1;193(1):49-53. Epub 2005 Nov 21. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16323131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-281760855"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murray CJ, Lopez AD, Chin B, Feehan D, Hill KH. Estimation of potential global&#x0000d;
pandemic influenza mortality on the basis of vital registry data from the 1918-20&#x0000d;
pandemic: a quantitative analysis. Lancet. 2006 Dec 23;368(9554):2211-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4066684272"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Conenello GM, Zamarin D, Perrone LA, Tumpey T, Palese P. A single mutation in 
the PB1-F2 of H5N1 (HK/97) and 1918 influenza A viruses contributes to increased 
virulence. PLoS Pathog. 2007 Oct 5;3(10):1414-21. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2000966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-486622969"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Conenello GM, Palese P. Influenza A virus PB1-F2: a small protein with a big
punch. Cell Host Microbe. 2007 Oct 11;2(4):207-9. Review. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2095877729"><mixed-citation>http://www.biohealthbase.org/GSearch/scienceSupport.do?decorator=Influenza</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3782600159"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Olson DR, Simonsen L, Edelson PJ, Morse SS. Epidemiological evidence of an&#x0000d;
early wave of the 1918 influenza pandemic in New York City. Proc Natl Acad Sci U &#x0000d;
S A. 2005 Aug 2;102(31):11059-63. Epub 2005 Jul 26. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1182402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36843574"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andreasen V, Viboud C, Simonsen L. Epidemiologic characterization of the 1918 &#x0000d;
influenza pandemic summer wave in Copenhagen: implications for pandemic control&#x0000d;
strategies. J Infect Dis. 2008 Jan 15;197(2):270-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2674012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1079708010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Serum cross-reactive&#x0000d;
antibody response to a novel influenza A (H1N1) virus after vaccination with&#x0000d;
seasonal influenza vaccine. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2009 May 22;58(19):521-4. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3872237679"><mixed-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moh.govt.nz/moh.nsf/indexmh/influenza-a-h1n1-update-138-18">New Zealand Influenza Surveillance</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4081367586"><mixed-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://knol.google.com/k/antoine-flahault/first-estimation-of-direct-h1n1pdm/2nsp4xxomyqub/1?collectionId=28qm4w0q65e4w.1">Knol: Estimation of H1N1pdm virulence</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1924325024"><mixed-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/flu/about/season/index.htm">CDC Influenza Surveillance</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-366374342"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2366616&#x00026;tool=pmcentrez">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2366616&#x00026;tool=pmcentrez</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3920945608"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Serfling RE, Sherman IL, Houseworth WJ. Excess pneumonia-influenza mortality&#x0000d;
by age and sex in three major influenza A2 epidemics, United States, 1957-58,&#x0000d;
1960 and 1963. Am J Epidemiol. 1967 Sep;86(2):433-41. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6058395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3750324927"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Barry JM, Viboud C, Simonsen L. Cross-protection between successive waves of&#x0000d;
the 1918-1919 influenza pandemic: epidemiological evidence from US Army camps and&#x0000d;
from Britain. J Infect Dis. 2008 Nov 15;198(10):1427-34. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-1355644555"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Morens DM, Taubenberger JK, Fauci AS. Predominant role of bacterial pneumonia &#x0000d;
as a cause of death in pandemic influenza: implications for pandemic influenza&#x0000d;
preparedness. J Infect Dis. 2008 Oct 1;198(7):962-70. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18710327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2599911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-379953419"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andreasen V, Viboud C, Simonsen L. Epidemiologic characterization of the 1918 &#x0000d;
influenza pandemic summer wave in Copenhagen: implications for pandemic control&#x0000d;
strategies. J Infect Dis. 2008 Jan 15;197(2):270-8.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://isds.cirg.washington.edu/distribute/">Distribute Surveillance System</ext-link> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2674012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3204547598"><mixed-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://isds.cirg.washington.edu/distribute/">Distribute Surveillance</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>